{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This composer incorporated the song \"Bright Sun, You Do Not Shine Equally\" into a piece to raise money for Red Cross agents helping Serbian casualties of an 1876 war with Turkey, his Marche Slave. For 10 points, name this Russian composer who depicted the Battle of Borodino turning back Napoleon from Moscow in his 1812 Overture.",
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Confederacy of thirteen of these places included eight “city” ones and five “forest” ones. Several of these places fought in the Kappel Wars, and the westernmost ones have been French- speaking for centuries. These places include Uri and Glarus, while in Graubunden, Romansh and German are spoken. For 10 points, name these geographical divisions that make up Switzerland.",
      "answer": "cantons of Switzerland"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fulk III of Anjou built dozens of a type of this structure called a donjon. An early version of this structure featured a motte (MAHT) and a bailey. One type of entrance to these structures was the barbican, which often included a portcullis. These structures centered on a keep and were surrounded by moats. For 10 points, name this type of fortification common in Medieval Europe.",
      "answer": "castles"
    },
    {
      "question": "After a 1515 French victory outside this city, the Swiss Confederacy swore an eternal truce with the French. This site of the Battle of Marignano was ruled by Ludovico il Moro, who commissioned Leonardo’s The Last Supper. Until falling under French and Spanish control, this city was ruled by the Sforza family. For 10 points, name this Northern Italian city.",
      "answer": "Milan"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to legend, Horatio Nelson’s body was stored in this substance after the Battle of\nTrafalgar. This product was created as a way to dispose of the molasses created as a byproduct of\nthe manufacture of sugar in the Caribbean. In the British Navy, Edward Vernon created the\npractice of diluting this substance with water. For 10 points, name this component of grog.",
      "answer": "rum"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Russian tsar freed the serfs in 1861 and was assassinated twenty years later?",
      "answer": "Alexander II"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader forcibly dismissed the Rump Parliament and replaced it with Barebone’s\nparliament. He was hated in Ireland for atrocities committed at Wexford and Drogheda. He\nhelped win the Battle of Naseby as a cavalry commander in the New Model Army. For 10 points,\nname this man who served as Lord Protector of England in the interregnum following the\nexecution of Charles I of England.",
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Cromwell",
        "Cromwell"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One painting of this event incorrectly includes Maria Letizia Ramolino. It was officiated by Pope Pius VII and held at Notre Dame de Paris, a conscious break from the traditional location of Reims. During this event, its subject surprisingly grabbed the crown and placed it on his own head. For 10 points, name this 1804 crowning of the first Emperor of the French.",
      "answer": "Coronation of Napoleon Bonaparte"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man orchestrated the starvation of millions of people in the Holodomor famine. The 1956 “Secret Speech” attacked this man for creating a personality cult. His foreign minister signed a non-aggression pact with Joachim von Ribbentrop, but joined the Allies after Germany invaded his country in 1941. For 10 points, name this Soviet dictator who succeeded Vladimir Lenin.",
      "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This project was supervised by \"Chief\" Thomas MacDonald, who implemented general directives such as the Phipps Act and Pershing Map. This project carved out an exception to its usual rules in Breezewood, Pennsylvania, and it was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who admired the German autobahn. For 10 points, name this national road network.",
      "answer": "Interstate Highway System"
    },
    {
      "question": "This dynasty accepted the surrender of the Kotte kingdom. The Kraak trade, begun late in this dynasty's rule, began exporting blue and white porcelain to Europe en masse. This dynasty scuttled its \"Treasure Fleet\" after sending out the expeditions of Zheng He. This dynasty fell to Manchu invaders in 1644. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty between the Yuan and Qing.",
      "answer": "Ming dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Brunswick Manifesto was proclaimed by this man’s cousin in an attempt to save this man’s life, and his son is known as the “Lost Dauphin”. This king’s wife was involved in the Affair of the Diamond Necklace, and his failure to consummate his marriage with that woman was due to his phimosis. After dismissing Jacques Necker, this monarch faced the Women’s March on Versailles, after which he was held captive in Paris. For ten points, name this husband of Marie Antoinette, a French monarch who was guillotined during the French Revolution.",
      "answer": "King Louis XVI"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man attempted to divest responsibility for causing a peasant war by writing Against the Murderous, Thieving Hordes of Peasants. He was sheltered by Frederick the Wise at Wartburg Castle, where he translated the New Testament into German. This man debated Ulrich Zwingli at the Marburg Colloquy and opposed the indulgences granted by men like Johann Tetzel. For ten points, name this father of the German Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization donated the SMS Goeben to the Ottoman Navy, and a rebellion by this organization in Kiel led to the end of the empire it served. Alfred Tirpitz sought to reform this organization, which used wolfpacks to attack British convoys. This organization made heavy use of the doctrine of unrestricted submarine warfare, and was led through WWII by Admiral Karl D¨onitz. For ten points, name this navy which used U-Boats during the two World Wars.",
      "answer": "German Navy"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Newcomen patented the first successful one of these devices, which was used to pump water out of mines. Hero of Alexandria’s aeliopile was a progenitor to this device, and John Smeaton created a competitor one of these products in England in the 1750s. Matthew Boulton worked to manufacture these devices with a man who installed a separate condenser to improve the efficiency of these devices. For ten points, name this invention, refined by James Watt, which provided power for the First Industrial Revolution in England.",
      "answer": "steam engine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Augustus the Strong was dethroned during this war, and one side in this war attacked in a blinding snowstorm, winning the Battle of Narva. The turning point of this war saw General Adam Lewenhaupt and his Caroleans defeated while attempting to storm the Great Redoubt. That battle forced the exile of the losing ruler, Charles XII. For ten points, name this war, mostly fought between Russia and Sweden, which saw the Battle of Poltava won by Peter the Great.",
      "answer": "Great Northern War"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a literary work, refugees from one of these events camp out at a villa in Fiesole [fee-AY-so-lay] for two weeks and tell stories that include one about “Patient Griselda.” People trying to stop this event wore masks with bird beaks, and the Flagellants gained notoriety for their self-abuse during this event. Boccaccio’s Decameron is set during, for ten points, what epidemic in the 1300s that killed over thirty percent of Europe’s population?",
      "answer": [
        "bubonic plague",
        "Black Death",
        "Black Plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The election of Daniel O’Connell led this man to pass the 1829 Catholic Relief Act. This man became Governor of Seringapatam after winning in the Fourth Anglo-Mysore War, and he later led forces at the Battle of Salamanca during the Peninsular War. Along with Gebhard von Blucher, this man won a battle that ended one French emperor’s return to power. For ten points, name this British general who won over Napoleon at Waterloo.",
      "answer": [
        "Duke of Wellington",
        "Arthur Wellsley",
        "Arthur Wesley"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In one battle fought in this state, British forces led by Charles Mawhood surrounded and killed Hugh Mercer after mistaking him for George Washington. At another battle in this state, the actions of Mary Hays may have inspired popular accounts of Molly Pitcher. The Hessian commander Johann Rall was killed at another battle fought in this state in December 1776 that was preceded by Washington’s crossing of the Delaware. For ten points, name this state home to the Revolutionary War battles of Princeton and Trenton.",
      "answer": "New Jersey"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1800s, Leslie Keeley discovered that a mixture of sodium and this element’s chloride was effective in treating addictions, including alcoholism. Fritz Haber suggested a way to pay off German war reparations by collecting this element from seawater. Geiger and Marsden disproved the plum pudding atomic model by bombarding alpha particles into a thin foil of this metal. For ten points, name this precious metal with chemical symbol Au.",
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, Davy Gam died while leading a band of knights in defense of his monarch. This battle was preceded by a lengthy siege of Harfleur. During this battle, the English used stakes to protect their archers from opposing cavalry and used longbows to devastating effect as the French cavalry trudged through a muddy battlefield. For ten points, name this victory for Henry V during the Hundred Years’ War.",
      "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people established a kingdom centered around Toulouse until they were forced out of France in the Battle of Vouille. The execution of the general Stilicho allowed these people to win a war against the weakened forces of Honorius. The emperor Valens was slain at Adrianople fighting against these people, who sacked Rome in 410 AD under the rule of Alaric. For ten points, name these Germanic peoples whose name implies that they came from the West.",
      "answer": "Visigoths"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an attempt to assassinate this ruler, Giuseppe Fieschi constructed a 25 barrel volley gun known as the Machine Infernale. This man’s Foreign Minister, Francois Guizot, fought with Lord Palmerston over the Spanish Queen Isabella II during the Affair of the Spanish Marriages. This King was frequently drawn as a pear by Honor´e Daumier [on-or-ay doh-me-ay]. This man came to power during the July Revolution and was overthrown in 1848. For ten points, name this French citizen king.",
      "answer": "Louis-Philippe I"
    },
    {
      "question": "A palace partially named for this color was the residence of British monarchs for most of the 16th and 17th centuries. William Adelin died in a disaster named after a ship of this color. The Ditchley Portrait shows Queen Elizabeth wearing an outfit of this color. A rose of this color was used to symbolize the House of York, as opposed to the red rose used by the House of Lancaster. For ten points, name this color of the chalk-laden Cliffs of Dover.",
      "answer": [
        "white",
        "Whitehall Palace, White Ship Disaster, white rose, White Cliffs of Dover"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two of these figures, Mushka and Pchyolka, were purposely killed in 1960 to prevent foreign powers from inspecting their vehicle. Strelka, another of these figures, gave birth to a child named Pushinka who was given as a gift to John F. Kennedy in 1961. The most famous of these animals was locked in a box for weeks of training and died of overheating after a separation failure, having completed four orbits aboard Sputnik 2. Laika was one of, for ten points, what trained animal cosmonauts?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet space dogs",
        "descriptive answers of “the dogs that the USSR launched into space",
        "promptonpartialanswers,suchas“dog”or“Soviets”or“Russians”or“cosmonaut”or“astronaut”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler gained control of Burgundy in the Treaty of Madrid shortly after defeating his rival at Pavia. He won the Battle of Muhlberg against the Schmalkaldic League while attempting to halt the Reformation in Germany, but eventually allowed for some religious autonomy in the Peace of Augsburg. This ruler summoned Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms. For ten points, name this 16th century monarch who served as both King of Spain and Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor",
        "Carlos I of Spain",
        "Charles I of Spain, but don’t"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One side in this battle benefited from the Dowding System, which used data from Chain Home stations to produce maps. Directive No. 17 ordered one side in this battle to begin with an assault on Adlertag, or Eagle Day. Failure in this battle led to the cancellation of Operation Sealion, prompting the statement of gratitude “never [...] was so much owed by so many to so few” from Winston Churchill. For ten points, name this air battle of 1940 in which the RAF defended their home from Nazi invasion.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Britain",
        "descriptions of Nazi Germany bombing any part of the United Kingdom, including England, London, etc.",
        "the Blitz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Domus Conversorum was a residence specifically built to house these people, many of whom died when Clifford’s Tower, the keep of York Castle, was burned to the ground in 1190. Oliver Cromwell ended a policy whereby these people had been banned from England since the reign of Edward I. The Balfour Declaration pledged support for the creation of a homeland for these people in the Middle East. For ten points, name this religious group whose British members have included Benjamin Disraeli.",
      "answer": "Jewish people"
    },
    {
      "question": "As Chancellor of the Exchequer, this politician introduced a budget that included the Cobden- Chevalier Treaty, lowering Anglo-French tariffs. As Prime Minister, he was able to secure the passage of a bill which benefited Irish tenants, but was never able to secure home rule during his four terms. This man’s Midlothian Campaign attacked his rival, a Conservative politician with a close friendship with Queen Victoria. For ten points, name this Liberal Prime Minister who feuded with Benjamin Disraeli.",
      "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of this event, the British government allowed the Kindertransport program to be set up by the Refugee Children’s Movement. A speech noting that demonstrations “should not be prepared or organized” but “are not to be hampered” helped fuel this event, which was triggered after Herschel Grynszpan assassinated diplomat Ernst vom Rath. SA Brownshirts carried out, for ten points, what massive attack on the night of November 9, 1938 against Jewish stores and synagogues in Germany?",
      "answer": "Kristallnacht or the Night of Broken Glass"
    },
    {
      "question": "ThismancommandedtheAgamemnon and,later,theCaptain underJohnJervisintheMediterranean fleet. An injury this man suffered at the Battle of Calvi left him blind in one eye; years later, this man claimed he didn’t see a signal to retreat after raising his telescope to that eye. A 169 foot tall Corinthian column in central London commemorates this man’s most famous battle, in which he was killed aboard the Victory. For ten points, name this British admiral who won the Battle of Trafalgar.",
      "answer": "Horatio Lord Nelson"
    },
    {
      "question": "An organization advocating this political ideology established its headquarters at Murphy Ranch under the leadership of William Dudley Pelley. Smedley Butler claimed that a conspiracy advocating this political ideology launched the Business Plot. The Silver Legion espoused this political ideology, sympathy for which was partially responsible for the cancellation of Father Coughlin’s radio show. For ten points, name this nationalist ideology held by American sympathizers of Germany and Italy in 1940.",
      "answer": [
        "fascism",
        "word forms, like fascist"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was fought concurrently with an engagement at Wavre [wahv], leading to the absence of Emmanuel Grouchy. This battle is commemorated by the Lion’s Mound, where a commander was shot off his horse. The arrival of Gebhard von Blucher’s Prussians helped turn the tide of this battle, which ended the Hundred Days and forced its loser into exile in St. Helena. For ten points, name this 1815 battle in which Wellington defeated Napoleon for the last time.",
      "answer": "Battle of Waterloo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. This action, as proposed in UN Resolution 181, was rejected by one side of the discussion. Haganah and the Irgun agitated for this action, whose early advocates included Theodor Herzl. The Balfour Declaration established British support for this action, whose eventual realization led to an outpouring of hundreds of thousands of refugees from the West Bank. A 1948 war accompanied, for ten points, what geopolitical action that followed the end of the British Mandate for Palestine?",
      "answer": [
        "creation of Israel",
        "equivalent descriptions",
        "descriptions of separate states for Jews and Palestinians or Jews and Arabs, etc. in Israel/Middle East"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these conflicts effectively ended with the capture of the Taku Forts. A letter that said, “Let us ask, where is your conscience?” was sent to the victorious monarch of these wars. One of these wars began when officials boarded and searched the Arrow. In the first of the Unequal Treaties, Hong Kong was ceded to the winner of these wars as part of the Treaty of Nanking. For ten points, name these 19th century wars in China over a British poppy export.",
      "answer": "Opium Wars"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Aboriginal activist William Cooper protested this event by giving a petition to a consulate in Melbourne. Herschel Grynszpan’s assassination of the diplomat Ernst von Rath sparked this event, which included the burning of hundreds of buildings, including the Fasanenstrasse Synagogue. For ten points, name this 1938 pogrom in Germany whose name translates to “Night of Broken Glass.”",
      "answer": [
        "Kristallnacht",
        "Night of Broken Glass before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was hurt by constant raids by the Victual Brothers against their signature cog ships. Though this group lost influence when the Steelyard was closed in England, they forced Valdemar IV to force the Treaty of Stralsund to gain greater trading rights in Denmark. This group was centered on Lubeck and formed by merchant guilds around North Germany. For ten points, name this Baltic merchant alliance active in the 14th century.",
      "answer": "Hanseatic League or Hansa"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ordered grapeshot to be fired on his own soldiers to win the tightly contested Battle of Guilford Courthouse. Though he often feuded with his superior Henry Clinton, this man was able to embarrass Horatio Gates at Camden. After one battle, this man claimed he was sick and sent his second in command, Charles O’Hara, to surrender instead. For ten points, name this British commander who was defeated by Comte de Rochambeau and George Washington at Yorktown.",
      "answer": "Charles Cornwallis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s son founded the first settlement by Spain in Uruguay while exploring the Rio de la Plata. The John Day letter recorded this man’s voyages, which were commemorated by a tower in Bristol, England. This man commanded the Matthew to Cape Bonavista. The Vikings had previously reached the land that this man explored, which lies near Cape Breton Island in Nova Scotia. For ten points, name this Genoan sailor who sailed for Henry VII to explore Canada for England.",
      "answer": "John Cabot or Giovanni Caboto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This treaty was signed by the British and Dutch after an agreement to terminate the successful Ostend trading company. This treaty was devised in an attempt to break an agreement of shared rule with Joseph I’s bloodline, the Mutual Pact of Succession. Since this agreement violated Salic Law, it was broken shortly after Charles VI’s death. For ten points, name this 1713 agreement that allowed for Maria Theresa to ascend the Habsburg throne.",
      "answer": "Pragmatic Sanction of 1713"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group’s second and final leader was Robert Greim, who was appointed to his post after covertly traveling to Tiergarten with Hanna Reitsch. This force, which was greatly expanded by Walter Wever and Albert Kesselring, employed the Ju-87 in Spain as part of the Condor Legion that bombed Guernica. Operation Sealion was canceled when this group was defeated by the RAF in the Battle of Britain. Hermann Goring led, for ten points, what Nazi air force?",
      "answer": "Luftwaffe"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man left law school after promising Saint Anna that he would change careers if he survived a lightning storm. Englishman William Tyndale was inspired by this man’s translation of the Bible into vernacular German. This man’s clashes with the ideology of Johann Tetzel led him to be brought before the Diet of Worms. For ten points, name this priest who protested the sale of indulgences by writing the 95 Theses, beginning the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was weakened after repeated attacks by Albert of Mecklenburg’s privateers and the Victual Brothers. As a result of the Treaty of Stralsund, Valdemar IV agreed to give this group control of the fish trade. This group’s cog ships helped carry out trades with outposts like the Steelyard, Visby, and Novgorod. Lubeck became known as the crown jewel of this group’s guilds. For ten points, name this German union that dominated medieval European trade.",
      "answer": "Hanseatic League or Hansa"
    },
    {
      "question": "At one battle, this ruler urged his men never to “lose sight of my panache” and noted that they were “on the road to honor and victory.” This man, who defeated the Duke of Mayenne at Ivry, was killed by Fran¸cois Ravaillac. The Guise faction in the French Wars of Religion was opposed by this king, who protected Protestant rights by proclaiming the Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this first Bourbon king of France who was a Huguenot before he converted to Catholicism, declaring “Paris is well worth a mass.”",
      "answer": [
        "Henry IV of France",
        "Henry III of Navarre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who fled to Crown Point after a battle in which his ships were destroyed by Guy Carleton, spread rumors that his force approaching Fort Stanwix was much larger than it really was. After the Battle of Lake Champlain, this husband of Peggy Shippen prompted Benjamin Franklin to scowl “Judas sold only one man,” but this man “[sold] three million.” For ten points, name this Revolutionary War general who tried to betray West Point to the British.",
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state promoted a traditional view of motherhood, one of many conservative reforms promoted as National Regeneration. A paramilitary group in this state called the Milice was headed by its Prime Minister, Pierre Laval. This state’s ships were attacked by the British while stationed at Mers el K´ebir and were scuttled in Toulon. This state revolved around the popularity of its president, Marshal Philippe Pet´ain. For ten points, name this puppet state that was established by the Nazis after the fall of France.",
      "answer": [
        "Vichy France",
        "French State"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man received a boost in the polls after he was accused of needing “some kind of Gestapo” to fulfill his policies. This man won an election on the slogan “Let Us Face the Future” and subsequently passed the National Insurance Act on the advice of the Beveridge Report. The British welfare state began under this man, who chartered the creation of the National Health Service. The Potsdam Conference was attended by, for ten points, what Prime Minister who replaced Winston Churchill at the end of World War II?",
      "answer": "Clement Attlee"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a book focusing on this event, Rosa Luxembourg described it as a “complete failure.” John Reed’s reporting on this event provided the basis for his book Ten Days that Shook the World. A blank was fired by the Aurora during an attack on the Winter Palace during this event, which occurred months after a Provisional Government was established following a similar event in February. The Bolsheviks planned, for ten points, what autumn 1917 Russian revolution?",
      "answer": [
        "October Revolution",
        "Russian Revolution of 1917 until “John Reed” is read, and prompt after",
        "Bolshevik Revolution until “Bolshevik” is read, and prompt after"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man became a Member of Parliament for Birmingham Ladywood, his first elected position, at the age of 49. This man recommended the abdication of Edward VIII, while serving as Chancellor of the Exchequer to Stanley Baldwin. On September 30, 1938, this man conceded the Sudetenland to Germany, and declared war on the latter after its invasion of Poland in 1939. For ten points, name this man, who served as Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1937 to 1940.",
      "answer": "Neville Chamberlain"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this action, the 78th Fraser Highlanders took heavy casualties from a French battery on the St. Charles River. This battle was preceded by an amphibious landing by the British at L'Anse-au-Foulon [[LAHNCE-oh-foo-LAWHN]]. The commanding generals, Louis Montcalm and James Wolfe, were both mortally wounded during this battle. For ten points, name this decisive 1759 battle, fought on the Plains of Abraham, where British troops captured a French-speaking city in Canada.",
      "answer": "Battle of Quebec or Battle of the Plains of Abraham before it is mentioned 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader, along with Maria Theresa and Prince Henry of Prussia, defeated and partitioned the Polish-Lithuanian Empire. This ruler also absorbed many lands of the Ottoman Empire and colonized Russian Alaska. This ruler’s personal collection of books and art was the foundation of what became the Hermitage Museum. This ruler came to power following a coup that unseated her husband and second cousin, Peter the Third. For ten points, name this Empress of All Russia.",
      "answer": [
        "Catherine the Great",
        "Catherine II"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A participant in this conflict named Rodrigo Diaz briefly switched sides after the Battle of Cabra and had a nickname meaning “the Lord.” Jews who did not flee this conflict were forced to become “conversos.” This event’s unofficial end came in 1492, when the Emirate of Granada fell to Spanish forces under the control of married Christian monarchs. For ten points, give the Spanish-language term for the expulsion of Muslims from Spain, led by Ferdinand and Isabella.",
      "answer": "Reconquista"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the early years of this route’s existence, ice-breaking ferries like the SS Angara provided a linkage over a large lake. In the early years of World War Two, this route was used to transport natural rubber from Southeast Asia to Europe, and Kurt Gödel [[GUR- duhl]] and Bette Erlich Lowenstein took this transportation line during their escape from Nazi Germany. The Circum-Baikal Railway was once part of, for ten points, what rail line that runs from Vladivostok to Moscow?",
      "answer": "Trans-Siberian Railway"
    },
    {
      "question": "A set of policies introduced by this leader led to the Thirty Glorious Years, an economic boom following World War Two. During the Empty Chair Crisis, this person ordered a withdrawal from the European Economic Community. This leader was targeted by a student uprising in May of 1968, during which his eventual successor, Georges Pompidou, negotiated on his behalf. The first president of the Fifth Republic was, for ten points, what leader of France during World War Two?",
      "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
    },
    {
      "question": "The site of these clashes is marked by eleven “witness houses,” as well as a stretch of Battle Road. A Daniel Chester French statue representing Captain Isaac Davis was unveiled at the centennial celebration of these battles. An annual reenactment staged by His Majesty’s 10th Regiment of Foot, along with volunteer militias from local Massachusetts towns, commemorates, for ten points, what pair of 1775 battles, legendarily started with the “shot heard ‘round the world’”?",
      "answer": [
        "Battles of Lexington and Concord",
        "in any order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. In 2012, Australian Trent Grimsey set the record time for this action, completing it in 6 hours and 55 minutes. Thomas Gregory is the youngest person to have achieved this feat, doing so at 11 years old in 1988. In 2019, British cancer survivor Sarah Thomas became the first person to successfully complete this action four consecutive times. In 1926, Gertrude Ederle, the “Queen of the Waves,” became the first woman to complete, for ten points, what long-distance European swim?",
      "answer": [
        "Swimming the English Channel",
        "descriptive answers including a swim across the English Channel,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While on his way to participate in this activity, Charles VIII of France died by striking his head on a lintel door. Members of the Third Estate vowed \"not to separate and to reassemble wherever necessary, until the Constitution of the kingdom is established\" in an \"Oath\" named for the location of this activity during the French Revolution. The aviator Roland Garros names a stadium in Paris dedicated to, for ten points, what sport, whose best players compete at the French Open and Wimbledon?",
      "answer": "Tennis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was sentenced to eight years of hard labor for criticizing Josef Stalin in a private letter. This man’s experience at Ekibastuz formed the basis for One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich. Although Khrushchev’s reforms freed this man from exile in 1956, the publication of his Cancer Ward and other works provoked the Soviet Union to revoke this man’s citizenship in 1974. For ten points, name this Russian Nobel Prize winner and author of The Gulag Archipelago.",
      "answer": "Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man succeeded Friedrich Ebert [[EE-buht]] as president of the Weimar [[VYE- mar]] Republic. Although he had won a spectacular victory at the Battle of Tannenberg, this man promulgated the “stab-in-the-back” theory regarding Germany’s defeat in World War One. In 1933, after years of resisting Hitler’s rise, this man felt he had no option but to appoint him as chancellor. For ten points, name this last pre-World War Two president of Germany, whose name christened an ill-fated airship.",
      "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sybil Ludington is nicknamed the “female” counterpart of this figure. William Dawes and this man were given similar tasks by Joseph Warren. This man’s most famous act occurred on “the eighteenth of April, in Seventy-Five” and is the subject of a Henry Wadsworth Longfellow poem that states \"one if by land, and two if by sea.\" For ten points, name this silversmith who warned of approaching British troops during a “midnight ride.”",
      "answer": "Paul Revere"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting of this ruler in his study shows a clock in the background at 4:13 a.m and a law code on a table. Paul Delaroche [[deh-lah-ROHSH]] painted a more realistic version of a painting where the names of Charlemagne and Hannibal can be seen on rocks below this leader. That painting by Jacques-Louis David [JAHK LOO-wee DAH-veed]] shows this ruler crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French Emperor depicted at battles like Austerlitz and Waterloo.",
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I of France 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The only known recording of this man is him repeating the first line of \"La Marseillaise\" in mocking French. The Ems Dispatch was purposefully released to the press by this man to discredit the government of Napoleon III. This minister annexed the province of Alsace-Lorraine following the Franco-Prussian War. The rise of Wilhelm II led to the deposition of, for ten points, which \"Iron Chancellor\" who masterminded the unification of Germany?",
      "answer": "Otto von Bismarck 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The winning side of this battle issued Order Number 227 before its start, commanding soldiers to take \"not a step back.\" Mamayev [[MAH-mah-yev]] Kurgan and Pavlov’s House were heavily contested locales during this battle. Romanian and German forces in this battle were encircled by Operation Uranus, led by Georgy Zhukov. For ten points, name this battle where Friedrich Paulus’s Sixth Army failed to take a city on the Volga named for the leader of the Soviet Union.",
      "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
    },
    {
      "question": "Polish forces deployed an armored variant of this product known as the \"FT-B\" in an effort to repel a Russian invasion during the 1920 Polish-Soviet War. The creator of this product joked that you can have it \"any color, so long as it is black\" during a board meeting. This was the most sold automobile of the early 20th century. The \"Tin Lizzie\" was a nickname for, for ten points, which first mass-produced car created by the Ford Motor Company?",
      "answer": "Ford Model T"
    },
    {
      "question": "A follower of the priest Iliodor [[ill-YOH-dor]] attempted to assassinate this man by stabbing him in the stomach. Another attempted assassination of this man involved feeding him cyanide-laced cake before he was finally killed with a bullet to the head by Felix Yusupov. This holy man claimed to have cured Alexei Romanov of hemophilia. For ten points, name this Russian mystic whose influence grew due to his closeness with Empress Alexandra.",
      "answer": "Grigori Yefimovich Rasputin"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a performance in this country of the ballet Spartacus by Aram Khachaturian [[kah-chah-TOO-ree-ahn]], Leonid Yakobson [[YAH-kohb-sun]] abandoned the traditional pointe technique during a performance at the Bolshoi Theatre. Ethnically Polish dancer Vaslav Nijinsky [[nih-JIN-skee]] helped popularize a ballet company named for this nation originally founded by Sergei Diaghilev [[dee-AH-geh-lef]]. Unrest occurred during the ballet The Rite of Spring, composed by, for ten points, what nation's composer, Igor Stravinsky?",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A passive walkout-turned-uprising in one of these places in Vorkuta [[vor-KOO-tah]] occurred in response to a mass influx of Ukrainians and the arrest of the repressive NKVD head Lavrentiy Beria [[law-REN-tee BEH-ree-ah]]. The Khrushchev Thaw led to the rehabilitation of many prisoners held in these camps first created by Lenin during the Russian Civil War. Many of the political opponents of the Great Purge were sent to, for ten points, what Soviet forced labor camps prominent in the Stalinist period?",
      "answer": [
        "Gulags",
        "Glávnoje upravlénije lageréj 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Tokyo Two were members of this group arrested for stealing cetacean meat. This organization was funded by an Irving-Stowe-arranged benefit concert at Amchitka. A ship belonging to it was docked at a New Zealand harbor when it was bombed by French agents; that ship was the Rainbow Warrior. For 10 points, name this militant environmentalist group",
        "answer": "Greenpeace"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other conservation group was founded by John Muir after a namesake mountain range?",
        "answer": "Sierra Club"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, French forces mutinied en masse following the failure of the Nivelle Offensive. Alexander Samsonov was killed during it when un-coded radio messages helped lead to the defeat of two Russian armies at Tannenberg. Anzac Day celebrates the Australians and New Zealanders who died during this war. For 10 points, name this 1914 to 1918 war.",
        "answer": "World War I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aside from Austria-Hungary and the Ottoman Empire, which other country in the Southeastern Balkans fought on the side of the Central Powers in World War I?",
        "answer": "Bulgaria"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "French citizens accused of this activity were often charged with “state of indignity.” Jozef Tiso was convicted and hanged for this crime in Czechoslovakia. The Épuration was a series of trials in France for this crime, of which Philippe Pétain and other leaders in the Vichy government were found guilty. For 10 points, name this crime of assisting an occupying army.",
        "answer": "Nazi collaboration"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What country's collaborationist regime was led by Vidkun Quisling and was the site of a heavy water plant intended for Germany's nuclear program?",
        "answer": "Norway"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was enflamed when a court-martial acquitted Ferdinand Esterhazy. One person\ninvolved in this scandal was imprisoned on Devil’s Island until key evidence against him was\nrevealed to be forged. Emile Zola wrote the letter J’Accuse supporting that prisoner. For 10\npoints, name this scandal in which a Jewish French army captain was framed for treason.",
        "answer": [
          "Dreyfus affair",
          "Dreyfus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another 19th century French political scandal concerned Ferdinand de Lesseps’\nattempts to build what structure?",
        "answer": "Panama Canal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's paper On the Description of Oval Curves came out when he was just 14. He created the first color photograph after showing the primacy of the RGB color system. His distribution of gas molecules was combined with the work of Ludwig Boltzmann. For 10 points, name this physicist who determined that light is a wave and formulated laws of electromagnetism.",
        "answer": "James Clerk Maxwell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "\"Maxwell's addition\" modified the circuit law discovered by what French namesake of the SI unit of electric current?",
        "answer": "Andre-Marie Ampere"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader mediated the Mediterranean Agreements of 1887. His struggle against the Catholic Church throughout the 1870s was known as the Kulturkampf. He instigated a war to take Schleswig and Holstein from Denmark, and used the Ems Dispatch to trigger the Franco- Prussian War. For 10 points, name this Prussian statesman who united the German Empire.",
        "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bismarck was forced to resign as chancellor by which German Emperor?",
        "answer": "Wilhelm II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The oldest event of this type in the U.S. takes place in Mobile, Alabama and is organized by groups such as the Mystic Stripers. Another of these events is organized by \"krewes\" (crews) who travel down St. Charles Avenue and Canal Street to avoid obstructions to floats in the French Quarter. For 10 points, name this day on which pre-Lent Carnival parades take place.",
        "answer": "Mardi Gras parades"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The New Orleans Mardi Gras flag contains gold, green, and what other color, whose \"Tyrian\" (TEER-ee-un) form was used to dye the togas of important Romans?",
        "answer": "purple"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Popular names for this event include an Gorta Mor and the Black 47. The simultaneous export of grain and meat products have labelled some historians to claim it was a genocide. This event was caused by an organism called phytophthora infestans or late blight. For 10 points, name this late 1840s event in which widespread crop failures caused mass starvation on a British island.",
        "answer": "Irish Potato Famine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Irish-English relations were further strained by what English land agent for Lord Erne who lends his name to a popular protest measure?",
        "answer": "Charles Cuunningham Boycott"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The leader who sent this force quipped that “He sent [this] against men, not God’s wind and waves”. This entity, which was directed by the Duke of Medina Sidonia, fared poorly against “Hell burners”, and was defeated at the Battle of Gravelines. This entity’s failure was attributed to the “Protestant Wind”, and it was sent to force one country to stop supporting Dutch rebels in the Eighty Years War. For ten points, name this massive naval fleet commanded by Phillip II whose goal was to invade England.",
        "answer": "Spanish Armada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This monarch, who gave the “Tilbury” speech to her troops, was the target of the Spanish Armada and the daughter of Henry VIII and Anne Boleyn",
        "answer": "Elizabeth I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Russian Ukase of 1821 violated this national policy with regards to Alaska. George Canning had originally proposed a joint effort to enact this decree, but it was rejected by John Quincy Adams. Richard Olney cited this policy to justify interference with British negotiations in the Venezuela Crisis. For ten points, name this decree opposing European intervention in the Western Hemisphere, named for the successor to James Madison.",
        "answer": "Monroe Doctrine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This President’s Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine allowed for intervention by the United States to overthrow “chronic wrongdoing” in Latin America.",
        "answer": "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “Plan West” defensive scheme was unsuccessful during this campaign, and the Battle of Mokra during this campaign saw a cavalry charge successfully repel a tank advance. The Gleiwitz incident was used as a pretense by one side in this conflict to launch an attack, and the “Phony War” followed this action. The Free City of Danzig was annexed after, for ten points, what September 1st, 1939 offensive that marked the beginning of World War II?",
        "answer": "Invasion of Poland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The invasion of Poland was facilitated by a Pact signed by Joachim von Ribbentrop and this man, the foreign minister of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": "Vyacheslav Molotov"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One man who performed this action reached Chur after being defeated in the Battle of Zurich; that man was Alexander Suvorov. Charlemagne is one of three names inscribed at the bottom of a painting depicting this action, as well as that of one man who passed Publius Scipio while performing this action. That man used the Lesser Saint Bernard Pass to perform this action, and ended up losing lots of elephants. For ten points, name this common action, where Napoleon and Hannibal led armies over a certain mountain range.",
        "answer": "crossing the Alps"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was falsely depicted on a charger in Napoleon Crossing the Alps, which was painted by this French neoclassicist, who also painted the Oath of the Horatii.",
        "answer": "Jacques-Louis David"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these events established a “right to work” advocated for by Louis Blanc, and included a separate instance of this type of event during it when the National Workshops were closed, known as the June Days. Another instance of this type of event saw the defeat of the Legitimists, and led to the July Monarchy. The most important event of this type saw the creation of the Constitutional Assembly and one part of it ended by the Thermidorian Reaction. For ten points, name this type of event, one of which began in 1789 and included the execution of Louis XVI.",
        "answer": [
          "Revolutions in France",
          "equivalents, including just French Revolution"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The June Days occurred during France’s revolution of this year, which also saw revolutions all across Europe. This year is sometimes known as the Spring of Nations.",
        "answer": "1848"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man commissioned Victor Baltard to renovate the market of Les Halles, and this man supported the Perriere brothers in forming the Cr´edit Mobilier. Derided by Victor Hugo, this man was inspired by Hyde Park to refurbish the Bois de Boulogne and the Bois de Vincennes as part of this man’s renovation of his capital, supervised by Baron Haussmann. This supporter of Emperor Maximilian of Mexico would be forced to abdicate after surrendering at the Battle of Sedan. For ten points, name this last emperor of France, nephew to the first.",
        "answer": "Napol´eon III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napol´eon III first rose to power by being elected president of this government, which overthrew the last king of France, Louis-Phillipe d’Orl´eans, in 1848.",
        "answer": "Second Republic of France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Little Willie prototype led to the development of male and female vehicles first used at the Battle of Flers-Courcelette. A plane called the “Scourge” was built during this war after the development of the interrupter. Other vehicles introduced during this war included the Sopwith Camel and the Fokker Dr.I, [d r 1] which was flown by the Red Baron. Tanks and airplanes revolutionized warfare in, for ten points, what early 20th century war, whose trench warfare was called to armistice in 1918?",
        "answer": "World War I or the Great War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This sulfur-containing chemical weapon was used by German forces near Ypres [ee-pruh] in 1917 to disable enemy soldiers. It burned the skin and contaminated the environment.",
        "answer": "mustard gas or sulfur mustard"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The rise of this political ideology was allegorized in the character of Arturo Ui, a mobster created by Bertolt Brecht. Gabriele D’Annunzio’s writings inspired the growth of this ideology, whose rise caused a split in the staff of the socialist newspaper Avanti! in Italy, where it developed during World War I. Bertolt Brecht fled his home country in 1933 in order to escape the rise of, for ten points, what political ideology, espoused in Nazi Germany by Adolf Hitler?",
        "answer": [
          "Fascism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hitler’s anti-Jewish and anti-communist views were detailed in this two-volume book, written in prison and published in the mid 1920s.",
        "answer": "Mein Kampf or My Struggle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s superiors forced him to agree to the Convention of Cintra; he was later court-martialed for it after his enemy escaped. This man’s victories at Salamanca and Vitoria were key in winning the Peninsular War and defending his ally, Portugal. This general fought Marshal Ney to a standstill at the Battle of Quatre-Bras two days before his troops, alongside Gebhard von Blucher, ended the Hundred Days campaign. For ten points, name this British general who won the Battle of Waterloo.",
        "answer": [
          "Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington",
          "either"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As a diplomat, the Duke of Wellington served as one of the British representatives to this 1815 conference, held to decide the status of Europe after the Napoleonic Wars. It was dominated by Austria’s Prince Metternich.",
        "answer": "Congress of Vienna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In case of war, this country planned to occupy its northern neighbor and advance to the Dyle River. After a regime change, this country’s allies attacked its navy, stationed at Mers-el-Kebir, despite the promises of Admiral Darlan to not let ships fall into enemy hands. After the siege of Calais [kah-lay], this country’s forces were evacuated by their British allies from Dunkirk. For ten points, name this country that was conquered by Germany during World War II after the fall of Paris.",
        "answer": [
          "France",
          "the Fourth Republic",
          "Vichy France only after “regime change” is said"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The French had constructed this defensive structure in event of a war with Germany, but it was bypassed when the Germans passed through the Ardennes Forest instead.",
        "answer": "Maginot Line"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author rebutted The Prince chapter-by-chapter in his Anti-Machiavel. He formed a league of princes known as the Fu¨rstenbund to protect Bavarian independence. This man signed the Convention of Westminister with Great Britain as part of the Diplomatic Revolution, and he entertained C.P.E. Bach and Voltaire at his palace of Sanssouci. For ten points, name this enlightened despot who ruled Prussia during the Seven Years War.",
        "answer": "Frederick the Great or Frederick II of Prussia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frederick the Great partitioned this European county with his Austrian and Russian neighbors, one of three partitions it suffered.",
        "answer": "Poland-Lithuania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person prepared a summary of his arguments, the Smalcald Articles, for a defensive alliance known as the Schmalkaldic League. This man, who broke with tradition by marrying Katharina von Bora, was condemned by the bull Exsurge Domine [ex-oor-gay doh-mee-nay] for actions taken after he objected to Johann Tetzel’s sale of indulgences. For ten points, identify this German monk who nailed his 95 Theses to a cathedral door, beginning the Protestant Reformation.",
        "answer": "Martin Luther"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Luther was condemned by Charles V at this 1521 meeting, where Charles issued an edict forbidding anybody to help Luther.",
        "answer": "Diet of Worms"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In response to this event, laywer Ludovic Trarieux [trair-you] created the Human Rights League. A bordereau central to this event was addressed to Max von Schwartzkoppen, the German military attach´e, promising state secrets. After the acquittal of this scandal’s real culprit, Ferdinand Esterhazy, Emile Zola attacked Felix Faure’s government with the open letter J’accuse. For ten points, name this scandal in which the French government wrongly imprisoned a Jewish artillery officer.",
        "answer": [
          "Dreyfus Affair",
          "equivalents for affair, like scandal"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dreyfus was imprisoned at the penal colony of Devil’s Island, located in this overseas French d´epartment. It is the site of most French rocket launches.",
        "answer": "French Guiana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This government was served by Nathalie Lemel’s Women’s Union. Members of this government destroyed the Vendˆome Column on the orders of the artist Gustave Courbet [core-bay]. Adolphe Thiers [tee-air] ordered Marshal MacMahon to violently end this government during the Bloody Week. Karl Marx argued that this government was an example of the dictatorship of the proletariat. For ten points, name this socialist government that, after the loss of the Franco-Prussian War, briefly ruled from the French capital.",
        "answer": "Paris Commune"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This palace, the home of French monarchs after 1564, was also destroyed during the Paris Commune. It shares its name with a garden in Paris adjacent to the Louvre.",
        "answer": "Tuileries Palace or Garden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Leo Amery attacked this man in Parliament by quoting Cromwell’s “In the name of God, go!” speech. This man was forced to resign after the failure of the expedition to Norway. He declared that there would be “peace in our time” after signing the Munich Agreement, part of his policy of appeasement towards Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this British prime minister who was succeeded by Winston Churchill at the beginning of World War II.",
        "answer": "Neville Chamberlain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chamberlain served in this position under his predecessor, Stanley Baldwin. Holders of this position in the United Kingdom manage the Treasury.",
        "answer": "Chancellor of the Exchequer"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A prelude to one of these wars was an attempt to kidnap the king known as the Amboise [am-bwahz] Conspiracy. During these wars, the Massacre of Vassy was orchestrated by the Duke of Guise [gheez]. One army in these wars was commanded by the prince of Cond´e and Gaspard de Coligny [co-lih-nee]. The phrase “Paris is well worth a Mass” was spoken by Henry IV, who ended the last of these wars by issuing the Edict of Nantes, promising toleration. For ten points, name this set of 16th century wars between Protestant Huguenots and Catholics in a certain country.",
        "answer": "French Wars of Religion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A major turning point during the French Wars of Religion was this 1572 mass killing of Huguenots, orchestrated by Catherine de Medici. Coligny was assassinated in this event.",
        "answer": "St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Duke of Ormonde oversaw Britain’s withdrawal from this war. After this war’s Battle of Denain, one side recovered much of its losses under the command of the duc de Villars. The duc de Tallard’s attempt to capture Vienna during this war was defeated at the Battle of Blenheim [blen-em]. The Duke of Marlborough and Eugene of Savoy commanded the winning alliance in this war against Louis XIV’s army. For ten points, name this conflict that ended when Philip V was recognized as king of a certain Iberian country.",
        "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the War of the Spanish Succession, the Duke of Ormonde was accused of treason for his alleged support of this 1715 uprising, which sought to restore the “Old Pretender” to the throne.",
        "answer": [
          "Jacobite rising of 1715",
          "Lord Mar’s Revolt"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man advocated for a “Common European Home” to prevent the threat of war from rival factions. This man, who removed Andrei Gromyko as foreign minister, began a policy of nonintervention known as the Sinatra Doctrine. The Gang of Eight targeted this man in a coup that was thwarted by a speech given atop a tank by Boris Yeltsin. The reforming policy of glasnost was championed by, for ten points, what final leader of the Soviet Union?",
        "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Sinatra Doctrine applied to the USSR’s allies within this defensive pact, a rival to NATO during the Cold War. ANSWER:Warsaw Pact(accepttheTreaty of Friendship, Cooperation, and Mutual Assistance) (5) Jedidiah Huntington led efforts to circumvent this law, which was succeeded by Macon’s Bill No. 2 shortly after its repeal. In a famous cartoon criticizing its effects, a man carrying a barrel labeled “super fine” attempts to break free of a snapping turtle’s grasp. The “Ograbme” cartoon attacked, for ten points, what 1807 legislation enacted by Thomas Jefferson that was intended to block trade with Great Britain and France?",
        "answer": [
          "Embargo Act of 1807 BONUS: The Embargo Act was a response to this British practice of forcing sailors to serve in its navy, done in 1807 to four Americans onboard the USS Chesapeake who the British claimed were defectors from their navy. ANSWER: impressment",
          "additional information, such as the press",
          "the press gang"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After Reinhard Scheer led this force at an indecisive battle near the Skagerrak, Scheer recommended that this force loosen its restrictions on attacking without warning. This military force was dismantled at Scapa Flow on Ludwig von Reuter’s orders, hoping that it would not be divided up between the victors after the Armistice. Alfred von Tirpitz revolutionized, for ten points, what military force that included the High Seas Fleet and which brought the US into World War I by sinking the Lusitania?",
        "answer": [
          "Imperial German Navy",
          "High Seas Fleet before mentioned",
          "mentions of German submarines after “restrictions” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alfred von Tirpitz assisted this Kaiser of Germany in the expansion of the Imperial German Navy. This man abdicated the throne after Germany lost World War I.",
        "answer": "Kaiser Wilhelm II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman’s note in The Times convinced Isambard Kingdom Brunel to build the Renkioi facility shortly after this figure arrived at the Selimiye Barracks. While working at Scutari, this woman cut the death rate in half after implementing techniques like hand-washing. This woman’s service in the Crimean War granted her the nickname “Lady with the Lamp.” For ten points, name this British woman, often considered the founder of modern nursing.",
        "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel designed several of these structures, including the Clifton one in Bristol. Another of these structures in London incorporates two blue and white towers.",
        "answer": [
          "suspension bridges",
          "Clifton Suspension Bridge",
          "Tower Bridge"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this empire’s colonial holdings was a company co-founded by Carl Peters and opposed by the failed Abushiri Revolt. This empire, which seized a naval base at Tsingtao from the Chinese in 1898, sent the Panther gunboat to Morocco in a failed attempt to break the Entente Cordiale alliance of two of its rivals. For ten points, name this country that engaged in a naval arms race with Great Britain and signed the 1879 Dual Alliance with Austria-Hungary, an alliance that lasted until they lost World War I.",
        "answer": "Germany or the German Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Germany’s African colonial history includes its genocide of the Herero people in this modern-day country in southwest Africa.",
        "answer": "Namibia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1341, a holder of this title instituted a salt tax called the gabelle. This title was promised to Henry V at the Treaty of Troyes and was split from the Kingdom of Navarre by Joan II. The next holder of this position was known as the dauphin. After 987, holders of this position were descended from Hugh Capet. For ten points, name this royal title held by eighteen different men with regnal name Louis.",
        "answer": "King of France"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The gabelle salt tax was abolished by this legislative body, which was formed by members of the Third Estate in summer 1789 in the buildup to the French Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "National Assembly or Assembl´ee Nationale",
          "National Constituent Assembly",
          "Assembl´ee Nationale Constituante"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character says that “a good heart” is more like the sun than the moon because it always shines brightly; that speech woos his future wife, who returns his affections in French because she cannot speak English. This character, who announces “Once more unto the breach, dear friends” at the siege of Harfleur, urges “We few, we happy few, we band of brothers” into battle in a fourth act speech. For ten points, name this Shakespearean character, an English king who marries Catherine of Valois after winning at Agincourt.",
        "answer": "Henry V"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “We band of brothers” quote derives from this Act IV speech, given by Henry V as his army prepares to fight the Battle of Agincourt.",
        "answer": "Saint Crispin’s Day speech"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler launched a military intervention to support John Zapolya against his rival Ferdinand I. Though this ruler signed the Treaty of Amasya to end an inconclusive war with the Safavid Empire, he was more successful in forcing the Knights Hospitaller out of Rhodes to gain control of the Mediterranean. This ruler was victorious at the Battle of Mohacs [moh-hotch] over Louis II of Hungary while expanding into Europe. For ten points, name this longest reigning Ottoman sultan, known as “the Magnificent.”",
        "answer": "Suleiman the Magnificent or Suleiman I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Suleiman’s campaigns were aided by this red bearded Ottoman admiral, who was victorious at the Battle of Preveza against the Holy League but lost Tunis to Charles V.",
        "answer": "Hayreddin Barbarossa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Margaret Keogh [kee-oh] is believed to be the first civilian killed during this event, shot by forces commanded by William Lowe. Eoin [”Owen”] MacNeill attempted to cancel this event, greatly reducing the turnout of Volunteers. One side in this event had headquarters in the General Post Office. Patrick Pearse and James Connolly were among those executed in Killingham Gaol [”jail”] for leading this event, which began with the proclamation of an independent republic. For ten points, name this 1916 uprising centered in Dublin on a certain holiday, which sought Irish independence.",
        "answer": [
          "Easter Rising of 1916",
          "equivalents like uprising, rebellion, etc., for rising"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was caught attempting to smuggle German arms to the Easter Uprising and executed. He had earlier authored a report detailing Belgian abuses in the Congo.",
        "answer": [
          "Roger Casement",
          "Casement Report"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler attempted to protect shipping from British warships by forming the League of Armed Neutrality. This ruler’s conquests were confirmed in the Treaty of Kuchuk-Kainarji, cementing the end of the Crimean Khanate. Three partitions of Poland were overseen by this ruler, who took power after her lover Grigory Orlov helped overthrow Peter III. For ten points, name this enlightened tsarina of Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Catherine the Great",
          "Catherine II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This kingdom joined the League of Armed Neutrality under the rule of Gustav III, who was assassinated in his capital of Stockholm.",
        "answer": "Sweden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A commander in this conflict successfully concluded a defense of his territory in the Treaty of Hubertusburg; that man nearly committed suicide after a loss at Kunersdorf, though he had earlier won a great victory at Rossbach in this war. This war was preceded by a change in alliances, in which France allied with Austria and Britain allied with Prussia, and it was ended by a 1763 Treaty of Paris. Frederick the Great participated in, for ten points, what expansive conflict that included the French and Indian War?",
        "answer": "Seven Years War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The change in alliances prior to the Seven Years War is historically known by this name.",
        "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This structure caused stations on the U6 and U8 to become known as ghost stops. Lucius Clay was appointed as an ambassador after the construction of this structure, and Egon Krenz oversaw its destruction. This structure, which was designed to prevent brain drain, included heavy military presence at locations like Checkpoint Charlie. For ten points, name this barrier that divided the modern capital of Germany during much of the Cold War.",
        "answer": "Berlin Wall"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Berlin Wall was opened in November of this year, one year before Germany was reunified and two years before the Soviet Union officially dissolved.",
        "answer": "1989"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began with light raids against shipping during the “storangriffe” period before culminating in a large scale strike on “Eagle Day.” Beta-carotene was used in propaganda as an explanation for why one side in this battle performed better at night. This battle led to the cancellation of the invasion plan Sealion and prompted the losing side to carry out the Blitz. For ten points, name this 1940 battle where the RAF thwarted the Luftwaffe over home airspace.",
        "answer": "Battle of Britain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Carrots didn’t win the Battle of Britain; instead, the Chain Home system used this novel technology to detect incoming German planes.",
        "answer": "Early Warning radar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This thinker’s most famous work was interpreted as a satire and as a deliberate misdirection by Diderot and Rousseau, respectively. This philosopher who analyzed Ab urbe condita in his Discourses on Livy, argued that it was best to begin ruling harshly so that everything seems kinder in comparison in his most famous work. It is better for a ruler to be feared than loved according to, for ten points, what early 16th century Italian diplomat, the author of The Prince?",
        "answer": "Niccolo Machiavelli"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Prince emphatically praises the politics of this leader, the son of Pope Alexander VI, who came from a prominent Italo-Spanish royal house.",
        "answer": "Cesare Borgia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began after one side marched through Normandy to provoke the Duke of Guyenne. A successful attack against the enemy baggage train in this battle was the only bright spot for the losing side, whose heavy cavalry was neutralized by heavy rains, mounted stakes, and English longbows. For ten points, name this 1415 battle, a victory for England in the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Agincourt was fought on October 25th, a feast day named in honor of this martyred Christian saint.",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Crispin",
          "Saint Crispin’s Day"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Theophilus Cotton ordered the splitting of this feature in order to allow a portion of it to be displayed more publicly. Alexis de Tocqueville wrote how this feature’s “very dust is shared as a relic.” Thomas Faunce was the first to describe the legend about this object that John Alden was the first person to have set foot on it. William Bradford’s history surprisingly omits any mention of, for ten points, what physical object where, in 1620, the pilgrims aboard the Mayflower supposedly set foot?",
        "answer": "Plymouth Rock BONUS:OnitswaytoAmerica,theMayflower wasaccompaniedbythissmallershipthatalsotransported pilgrims. ANSWER: Speedwell 4 Yakov Zhilinsky was blamed for giving overaggressive orders in this battle. Max Hoffmann predicted that Alexander Samsonov and Paul von Rennenkampf would refuse to help each other during this battle, which was followed by an engagement at the Masurian Lakes. This battle was named after a battle 500 years earlier to “avenge” a loss at Grunwald. Erich Ludendorff rose to fame after, for ten points, what 1914 battle where Paul von Hindenburg defeated a Russian force? ANSWER: Second Battle of Tannenberg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “first” Battle of Tannenberg, fought near Grunwald in 1410, was a loss for this Germanic group that formed in the 12th century. This group still gives honorary knighthoods today.",
        "answer": [
          "Teutonic Knights or the Teutonic Order",
          "the Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician declared “There is no place for the state in the bedchambers of the nation” before decriminalizing homosexuality. This politician, who once claimed that he had used the words “fuddle duddle” when a journalist questioned him for swearing in Parliament, made French and English equal under the Official Languages Act in 1969, one of the first accomplishments in his over 15 years as Prime Minister. For ten points, name this Canadian politician who was the father of Canada’s current PM.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the 1970 October Crisis, Pierre Trudeau gave this laconic reply to a reporter who asked “How far would you go with that?” in restricting civil liberties to maintain the peace.",
        "answer": "Well, just watch me."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s resignation was commemorated by the Mischianza Party. In an early battle, this man moved his troops across the Verrazzano Narrows shortly before outflanking the Guan Heights. This man resisted an attack at Germantown shortly after winning the Battle of Brandywine. Though he was victorious at Long Island and later captured Philadelphia, this man resigned and was replaced by Henry Clinton. For ten points, name this British commander who was victorious at Bunker Hill.",
        "answer": "William Howe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In September 1775, William Howe took over command of all British forces in America from this man, who then returned to Britain.",
        "answer": "Thomas Gage"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A cartoon satirizing this program shows a group of leaders dressed as Boy Scouts marching in front of a bus with the word “Ruin” printed on it. Hjalmar Schacht was the president of an institution reorganized by this program. A $200 million loan was provided as part of this plan, which created the Reichsmark. Owen Young named a successor to this program that included a twenty percent reduction in certain debts. For ten points, name this 1924 plan intended to help Germany pay its World War I reparations.",
        "answer": "Dawes Plan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The reparations owed by Germany were legally laid out in part 8 of the Treaty of Versailles, which opens with this highly controversial statement assigning all loss to German causes. This article is often cited as a precursor to the rise of Nazi aggression.",
        "answer": "Article 231 or the War Guilt Clause"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Near the end of Queen Anne’s War, riots named for this commodity in Boston led to the poor breaking the rudder of a ship owned by merchant Andrew Belcher. To offset the development of rickets in the UK, the government added calcium to this food during World War II. Juvenal likely coined a term for appeasement of the masses by pairing this food with circuses. Marie Antoinette was said to have proclaimed “Let them eat cake!” during a shortage of, for ten points, what staple baked food?",
        "answer": "bread"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Flour War broke out among French peasants during the reign of this king, the husband of Marie Antoinette.",
        "answer": "Louis XVI"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This piece was premiered in a tent outside the unfinished Cathedral of Christ the Saviour. The tambourine and English horn introduce the folk-tune “At the Gate, At My Gate” in this piece, which opens with four cellos and two violas playing the hymn “Oh Lord, Save Thy People.” This piece’s use of “La Marseillaise” is overtaken by “God Save the Tsar,” during which live cannons fire. The Battle of Borodino is commemorated by, for ten points, what Tchaikovsky overture named for the year of Russia’s victory over France?",
        "answer": [
          "1812 Overture",
          "The Year 1812"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Cathedral of Christ the Saviour was built in this Russian city. Stalin ordered the cathedral torn down to build a new Palace of the Soviets, which was scrapped during World War II.",
        "answer": "Moscow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was attacked by “hellburners” near Flanders prior to the Battle of Gravelines. A queen declared that she possessed “the heart and stomach of a king” while rallying resistance against this group in the Tilbury Speech. Sir Francis Drake bragged that he had “singed the beard” of the king after striking this group at Cadiz. Elizabeth I was to be replaced by a Catholic ruler after an attack by, for ten points, what fleet that failed to subdue England in 1588?",
        "answer": "Spanish Armada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This king of Spain, a son of Charles V, sent the Armada.",
        "answer": "Philip II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the short-lived first of these wars, a group of regulars lost a quarter of their men to sharpshooters led by Piet Joubert at Laing’s Nek. Between the two of these wars, Alfred Beit helped orchestrate the Jameson Raid in an attempt to overthrow Paul Kruger. Louis Botha and Jan Smuts participated in the second of these wars as leaders of the Transvaal. The British fought in, for ten points, what wars against the namesake Dutch settlers of South Africa?",
        "answer": [
          "Boer Wars",
          "First and/or Second Boer Wars"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term was applied to refugee camps established by the British during the Second Boer War, where tens of thousands of Boers died, many of measles and typhoid.",
        "answer": "concentration camps"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This initiative was brought into effect by the Berlin Decree and subsequently escalated by the Orders in Council, which prompted Scandinavian nations to form the Second League of Armed Neutrality. Following the Battle of Friedland and the signing of the Treaty of Tilsit, one nation joined this initiative; however, that nation later deserted this system, prompting a French invasion of Russia. For ten points, name this Napoleonic system that attempted to impose an economic blockade on Great Britain.",
        "answer": "Continental System"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Portugal’s refusal to join the Continental System ultimately led to this war in 1808. It included the Battle of Salamanca.",
        "answer": "Peninsular War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This settlement was led by Ralph Lane until a rough storm convinced him to return home with Francis Drake. Virginia Dare, the first English child to be born in the New World, was born at this settlement. John White was sent to resupply this settlement, but an oak tree with the word CROATOAN scrawled into it was discovered instead. For ten points, name this North Carolina colony whose settlers mysteriously disappeared.",
        "answer": "Roanoke Colony"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Roanoke Colony was a project funded by this Englishman. In 1595, this Englishman searched for El Dorado in Guiana, having left on the pretense of trying to find the lost colonists.",
        "answer": "Sir Walter Raleigh"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Through their contact with China, these people introduced the seax shortsword to Western Europe, and they adopted the Alani practice of lengthening of the skull of infants born to noblemen. These people lost the Battle of Nedao, and a coalition of the Visigoths led by King Theoderic and Romans under Flavius Aetius defeated these people at the Battle of Catalaunian Fields in 451 AD. For ten points, name these nomadic people led by the so-called “Scourge of God,” Attila.",
        "answer": "Huns"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This pope, the first of his name, is given credit for negotiating with Attila to end his invasion of Italy in 452.",
        "answer": "Leo the Great or Leo I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Max Nordau promoted this movement in an address calling for a “muscular” version of its supporters. Ze’ev Jabotinsky founded a “revisionist” version of this movement with the creation of Betar. The Uganda Scheme tried to give up a portion of British East Africa in support of this movement. The Balfour Declaration, given to Lord Rothschild, reaffirmed this movement’s desire for aliyah. For ten points, name this movement that, at its creation in the 19th century, sought to establish a Jewish homeland in Israel.",
        "answer": "Zionism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This activist founded the Zionist Organization at an 1897 conference in Switzerland and is often known as the “father” of modern Israel.",
        "answer": "Theodor Herzl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A former member of this movement named Jeremiah Brandreth led the failed Pentrich Rising, which wanted to wipe out the national debt by starting an uprising in Derbyshire. This movement’s namesake, a weaver in Anstey, used a hammer in his most notorious act. The Frame Breaking Act of 1812 allowed the British government to execute seventy members of this movement, which began in Nottingham among textile workers worried about their job security. For ten points, name this 19th century movement that violently opposed innovation and lends its name to a modern term for people that do not embrace new technology.",
        "answer": "Luddites"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the supporters of the Luddites was this father of computer programming pioneer Ada Lovelace.",
        "answer": "Lord George Gordon Byron"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man died on a diplomatic mission to Russia after his ship, the HMS Hampshire, hit a German mine. This man’s infighting with George Curzon caused Curzon to resign as Viceroy of India. This man agreed with Jean-Baptiste Marchand to fly three flags over an African fort during a tense territorial standoff in 1898. A 1914 recruitment poster demanded that this man “wants you” to join the army. Charles Gordon’s death was “avenged” by, for ten points, what British officer who won the 1898 Battle of Omdurman in Sudan?",
        "answer": "Horatio Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kitchener helped resolve this 1898 dispute between England and France over the Sudan through calm, restrained relations with his French counterpart, Jean-Baptiste Marchand. Britain’s massive troop advantage also helped ensure this incident did not explode into war.",
        "answer": "Fashoda incident or crisis, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Churches named for this commodity dotted East Anglia in England and were named due to the largest donations coming from rich local merchants. “Owlers” smuggled this good out of England. In 1378, workers of this industry fought to form a government of disenfranchised craftsmen in Florence after leading the Ciompi Rebellion. The Navigation Acts banned the American colonies from buying this textile commodity except from England. Mohair and angora are types of, for ten points, what textile that is most commonly sheared from sheep?",
        "answer": "wool"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the more notable Wool Churches is St. Agnes’ Church in this eastern English county, which shares its name with a Virginia city in the Hampton Roads region.",
        "answer": "Norfolk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This object gained a nickname after a leader promised, “we’ll show you!” at a United Nations assembly, leading it to become known as “Kuzma’s mother.” A Tu-95V was equipped with reflective white paint to protect Andrei Durnovtsev during a test of this object, which built on the RDS-37 design. This object was tested at Severny Island in Novaya Zemlya, releasing 51 megatons of energy. For ten points, name this Soviet bomb, the strongest nuclear weapon ever detonated.",
        "answer": "Tsar Bomba"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The team that built Tsar Bomba included this Russian physicist who became a disarmament peace activist shortly thereafter. The European Parliament awards an annual prize for Freedom of Thought named after this man.",
        "answer": [
          "Andrei Sakharov",
          "Sakharov Prize"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Major Hubert-Joseph Henry made a dramatic testimony during this event in which the Panizzardi telegram was investigated. Armand du Paty de Clam was promoted in this event, which was resolved when Henri Brisson resigned. Émile Zola wrote J'Accuse during this event, increasing public pressure to reopen it. The real traitor in this event was Ferdinand Esterhazy. For ten points, name this French scandal in which a Jewish officer was wrongly convicted.",
        "answer": "Dreyfus Affair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the \"Dreyfusards\" who supported Major Dreyfus during his re-trial was this Minister of the Interior and later Prime Minister of France, nicknamed \"The Tiger.\"",
        "answer": "Georges Clemenceau"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Guntram, a leader of these people signed the Pact of Andelot. One noble of these people tried to kill Rigunth by slamming a chest shut, and that woman, Fredegund, also ordered Sigebert I's assassination. A queen of these people, Brunhilda, was executed by being pulled apart by horses. Gregory of Tours documented these people's Merovingian Dynasty. Pepin the Short and Clovis were rulers of, for ten points, what Germanic people who gave their name to France?",
        "answer": [
          "Franks",
          "Merovingians Dynasty before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Merovingian kingdom extended as far east as what is today this largely Catholic German state, an independent kingdom from 1806 to 1871, whose largest city is Munich.",
        "answer": "Free State of Bavaria 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group fought Valdemar IV of Denmark after he sacked Visby on the island of Gotland. Crews in this group were called Schiffskinder, and the Bay Fleet travelled from the English Channel to trade with this group. The Victual Brothers were initially supported by this group. This league's trading ports were called Kontors, and its member cities included Hamburg and Lübeck. For ten points, name this league of merchant states along Northern Europe and the Baltic sea.",
        "answer": [
          "Hanseatic League",
          "Hansa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the most noted citizens of Lübeck was this Nobel Prize-winning leader of the Social Democratic Party of Germany who served as Chancellor of Germany from 1969 to 1974.",
        "answer": "Willy Brandt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Paul Coe helped found a legal service for these people in 1970. Stockmen and house servants from these people participated in the Wave Hill walk-off. The doctrine of \"terra nullius\" was replaced with the right of \"native title\" for these people in Mabo v. Queensland. Many of these people hold to The Dreaming, and Uluru is sacred to those known as the Alangu among these people. Torres Strait islanders are generally considered distinct from, for ten points, which people from places like Tasmania and the Outback?",
        "answer": [
          "Aboriginal Australians",
          "answers including Aborigines and Australia,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1873, William Gosse became the first European to site Uluru, and he gave it this English name in honor of the Chief Secretary of South Australia at the time.",
        "answer": "Ayers Rock"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to Werner Sombart, a period named for this material formed during the pre-industrial phase. Shortages of this material are noted in German history as the Holznot, and Joachim Radkau’s history of this material claims that fear of a lack of this material led to modern environmentalism. Huge rafts of this material were sent to the Netherlands for shipbuilding after having been extracted from the Black Forest. For ten points, excessive use of what material in Germany caused deforestation?",
        "answer": [
          "Wood",
          "Trees, Timber, and other similar answers relating to wood"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many trees were felled at the Lüneburg Heath for the extraction of this substance. A former mine for this substance at Wieliczka [[vee-eh-LEECH-kah]], Poland contains St. Kinga's chapel, an underground lake, and statues carved of this material.",
        "answer": [
          "Salt",
          "NaCl",
          "or Sodium Chloride"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Welshman Davy Gam was killed in this battle, during which nobles from Picardy and Artois were killed en masse. Taking tactics from the Battle of Nicopolis, the winners of this battle planted stakes for defense. Deep mud and heavy armor impaired one side at this battle, allowing for archers to cut down men-at-arms. Shakespeare’s rendition of this Saint Crispin’s Day battle included the “Band of Brothers” speech, given by this battle’s victorious King Henry V of England. For ten points, name this 1415 battle during the Hundred Years' War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charles VI of France reigned for 42 years but was not present for the defeat at Agincourt, perhaps due to mental incapacity that earned him this nickname.",
        "answer": "The Mad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Glorioso survived attacks at the Azores and Cape Finisterre with millions of silver dollars on board. Sardinian forces defended Villafranca in this war, and George Townshend also blockaded Genoa. Fog and snow, as well as inexperience, did not stop Frederick the Great from winning at Mollwitz during this war. After this war ended with the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle, Prussia allied with Britain in the Diplomatic Revolution. For ten points, name this war that challenged Maria Theresa's right to inherit the Hapsburg Empire.",
        "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Austrian Succession also saw the last command of troops in combat by a reigning British monarch when this king led his men at Dettingen.",
        "answer": "George II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Old Vineyards were attacked at this battle, and during this battle, the sun overcame the fog, allowing St. Hilaire's men to attack the heights. A general at this battle said, “One sharp blow and the war is over.” Artillery broke the ice at this battle, causing men to drown in the Satschan ponds. This battle featured an attack on the Pratzen Heights and led to the creation of the Confederation of the Rhine and the signing of the Treaty of Pressburg. Russians and Austrians lost to Napoleon in, for ten points, what 1805 battle?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Austerlitz",
          "Battle of the Three Emperors"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This last Holy Roman Emperor lost at the battle of Austerlitz and subsequently married his daughter Marie Louise, Duchess of Parma, to Napoleon.",
        "answer": "Francis II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This house was founded by John of Fond Memory, and one of this house's rulers governed as Peter the Constable. António, Prior of Crato, tried to lead this house, though he lost the Battle of Ponta Delgada. This house's members included Ferdinand the Holy Prince who, as part of the \"illustrious Generation,” attacked Tangier with his brother, Henry the Navigator. The last ruler of this house was followed by a union with Spain under Philip II. For ten points, name this Portuguese house.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Aviz",
          "Joanine Dynasty"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John II, of the House of Aviz, worked with Spain to separate their New World discoveries from Portugal's through this 1494 treaty.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Tordesillas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Earl Grey tea is named for one holder of this position, while another names the capital of the Australian state of Victoria. A Canadian, Andrew Bonar Law, held this position for 211 days between 1922 and 1923. As a result of the Brexit controversy, Theresa May resigned from this position in July 2019. For ten points, name this position, held since 2019 by Boris Johnson from 10 Downing Street, the head of the British government.",
        "answer": [
          "Prime Minister of the United Kingdom",
          "British Prime Minister",
          "Great Britain in place of \"United Kingdom\"",
          "PM in place of \"Prime Minister\"",
          "UK in place of \"United Kingdom\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Since 1902, the prime minister has almost exclusively been the majority leader of this body, the lower house of British Parliament, which meets at the Palace of Westminster alongside the House of Lords.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Commons",
          "The Commons",
          "formally: The Honourable the Commons of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in Parliament assembled"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The preaching background of this party's first leader led Morgan Phillips to comment, \"Socialism in Britain owed more to Methodism than Marx.\" That founder of this party, Keir Hardie, resigned in favor of Arthur Henderson, who won the Nobel Peace Prize for chairing the Geneva Disarmament Conference. This party interrupted Winston Churchill's term as prime minister under the leadership of Clement Attlee. For ten points, name this currently center-left British political party, the opponent of the Conservatives.",
        "answer": "Labour Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Under the Attlee government, Labour minister Aneurin Bevan [[uh-NYE-rin BEH- vahn]] developed this government system that publicly funds hospitals and other social services throughout the United Kingdom.",
        "answer": "National Health Service or NHS"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler approached his cousin of the same name to force him to become dictator, though that Grand Duke responded by pointing a pistol at his own head and threatening to fire. That episode occurred during the Revolution of 1905, in which this ruler's forces fired on demonstrators during \"Bloody Sunday\" at the Winter Palace. The Russo-Japanese War was lost by, for ten points, which Tsar who was later killed by the Bolsheviks?",
        "answer": [
          "Nicholas II",
          "Nikolai II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nicholas II's reforms during the Revolution of 1905 created this parliamentary body of Russia, the name of which is still carried by the lower house of Russian parliament.",
        "answer": [
          "State Duma or Imperial Duma",
          "Imperial State Duma",
          "Gosudarstvennaya Duma 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one poem, William Wordsworth referred to this site as an \"Inmate of lonesome Nature's endless year.\" After stabbing Alec, Tess of the D'urbervilles finally surrenders to police at this monument, which lies in Wiltshire. The works of William Stukeley led to the popular connection between this monument and the order of druids. For ten points, name this prehistoric monument on the Salisbury Plain that is often featured in British literature.",
        "answer": "Stonehenge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In a radio serial, this fictional detective investigates the death of a Presbyterian minister at Stonehenge. This character's aide was wounded while fighting in Afghanistan during the Great Game era.",
        "answer": "Sherlock Holmes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A thinker from this country criticized the Gotha [[GOH-tah]] Programme of its Social Democratic Party in one pamphlet. Another thinker from this country argued that a “Protestant work ethic” enabled the development of modern capitalism and suggested that the state held a monopoly on the legitimate use of violence. Two writers originally from this country wrote the Communist Manifesto. For ten points, name this homeland of Friedrich Engels, Max Weber [[VEH-buh]], and Karl Marx.",
        "answer": [
          "Germany or Deutschland",
          "German Reich",
          "or Deutsches Reich",
          "the Kingdom of Prussia",
          "Königreich Preußen"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This German philosopher, who stated \"God is dead,\" suggested that human history changed when people went from thinking of \"good and bad\" to \"good and evil.\"",
        "answer": "Friedrich Nietzsche ] or Friedrich Wilhelm Nietzsche"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "It's not Portugal, but The Lusiads inspired this nation's opera L'Africaine [[lah-free- KEHN]], about the historical Vasco da Gama. A member of this nation's Les Six [[LEH SEE]] was inspired by the martyrdom of a convent of nuns to write his Dialogues of the Carmelites. The composer of The Carnival of the Animals was from this nation, as was the composer of Clair de Lune. For ten points, name this European nation, home to composers like Camille Saint-Saëns [[kah-MEEL san-SAHN]] and Claude Debussy [[klohd deh-byoo-SEE]].",
        "answer": [
          "France",
          "First French Empire",
          "Second French Empire",
          "French Second Republic",
          "French Third Republic"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Georges Bizet [[bee-ZEH]], another French composer, set this opera in the historical bull-fighting scene of the south of Spain.",
        "answer": "Carmen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A poet from this nation named Pulci [[POOL-chee]] retells an account of Charlemagne’s paladins, Roland [[roh-LAHND]] and Renauld [[reh-NOHD]] who convert the title Morgante [[mor-GAHN-teh]] to Christianity. William of Baskerville solves a murder in a Benedictine monastery in this country in The Name of the Rose by Umberto Eco [[EH-koh]]. Cesare Borgia's [[CHEH-zeh-reh BOR-zhahs]] military exploits inspired Niccolo Machiavelli to write The Prince, in, for ten points, what is now what country?",
        "answer": [
          "Italy",
          "Italian Republic",
          "Italia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dario Fo wrote the Italian-language play Isabella, Three Sailing Ships and a Con Man to demystify the narrative around this 15th-century explorer.",
        "answer": [
          "Christopher Columbus",
          "Cristoforo Colombo",
          "or Cristóbal Colón"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One ruler of this name became the last British monarch to lead an army in the field at the Battle of Dettingen [[deh-TIN-gehn]]. Robert Walpole became the first British prime minister under a ruler of this name after the South Sea Bubble burst. Another ruler of this name suffered from a mental illness believed to be porphyria [[por-\"FEAR\"-ee-ah]] and was king during the American Revolution. For ten points, give this name of four 18th and 19th- century British monarchs.",
        "answer": [
          "George",
          "George I",
          "or George II",
          "or George III"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The four Georges on the British throne were all from a dynasty named for this German state, which came to power after the death of Queen Anne.",
        "answer": "Hanover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man established a short-lived Government-in-exile known as the Sigmaringen Enclave. During one conflict, this man's defensive strategy prevented mass mutinies following the disastrous Nivelle Offensive against Imperial Germany. A cabinet led by this man formally surrendered to Nazi Germany during the Peace at Compiègne [[cohm-pee- EHN]] following a 1940 blitzkrieg. For ten points, name this Marshal of France who led the collaborationist Vichy Regime.",
        "answer": "Philippe Pétain ] or Henri Philippe Benoni Omer Pétain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both Prime Minister Clemenceau and Marshal Pétain disliked this other French general, who took Supreme Command of Allied Forces during the surprise German Spring Offensive of 1918 and later accepted the German cessation of hostilities.",
        "answer": "Ferdinand Foch"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ANGLO-SAXON ENGLAND",
      "prompt": "During England's Anglo-Saxon period, which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "type of seafaring Scandinavian raiders often raided the coast?",
          "answer": "Vikings"
        },
        {
          "question": "king of Wessex was called \"the Great\"?",
          "answer": "Alfred the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "1066 battle began William the Conqueror’s conquest of England?",
          "answer": "Battle of Hastings"
        },
        {
          "question": "language was used to compose the poem Beowulf?",
          "answer": "Old English"
        },
        {
          "question": "position, later held by Thomas Beckett, was created by the missionary Augustine?",
          "answer": "archbishop of Canterbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "nickname was given to King Aethelred after his defeat by Sweyn Forkbeard?",
          "answer": "unready"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Venerable\" monk authored an Ecclesiastical History of the English People?",
          "answer": "The Venerable Bede"
        },
        {
          "question": "king was killed by Norman forces at the Battle of Hastings?",
          "answer": "Harold Godwinson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EUROPEAN CITIES IN THE 1940’s",
      "prompt": "Which European city...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the site of an airlift into the city's Soviet zone in 1948?",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was where military tribunals were held to try Nazi leaders?",
          "answer": "Nuremberg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a conference where the United States, Great Britain, and the Soviet Union agreed to divide Germany into four occupation zones?",
          "answer": "Potsdam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the largest battle in history and repulsed the German army from its invasion of the Soviet Union?",
          "answer": "Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the largest Jewish ghetto uprising against the Nazis in 1943?",
          "answer": "Warsaw"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a massive evacuation of Allied troops to Great Britain?",
          "answer": "Dunkirk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city where Ernest Hemingway claimed to liberate the bar at the Ritz hotel in 1944?",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city where the Nazis failed to destroy the Ponte Vecchio (PON-tay VEK-ee-yo) over the Arno River?",
          "answer": "Florence"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE FRENCH REVOLUTION",
      "prompt": "During the French Revolution, what",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "King of France was guillotined?",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Queen of France apocryphally said “let them eat cake.”?",
          "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Committee of Public Safety was turned on during the Thermidorian Reaction?",
          "answer": "Maximilien de Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary was killed in his bath by Charlotte Corday?",
          "answer": "Jean-Paul Marat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oath was sworn by the National Assembly after it was locked out of its planned meeting space?",
          "answer": "Tennis Court Oath"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three values were enshrined in the national motto of Revolutionary France?",
          "answer": "Liberté, égalité, fraternité"
        },
        {
          "question": "Seventeen article charter of human rights was adopted by the National Assembly in 1789?",
          "answer": "Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Province had a namesake Royalist counterrevolution from 1793-1796?",
          "answer": "the Vendee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE CONGRESS OF VIENNA",
      "prompt": "During or after the Congress of Vienna, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French emperor was exiled to Saint Helena?",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "Napoleon",
            "Napoleon I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesmen hosted the forum?",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who was victorious at Waterloo joined Castlereagh in representing the UK?",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Wellesley",
            "Wellesley",
            "the Duke of Wellington",
            "Wellington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Czar of Russia led the Russian delegation?",
          "answer": "Alexander I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country retained control of the Cape Colony and Tobago?",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Minister for Louis XVIII headed the French delegation?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand",
            "Talleyrand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country regained control of Tyrol and Ragusa?",
          "answer": "Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country was represented by Cael Lowenhielm, an illegitimate son of its king Charles XIII?",
          "answer": "Sweden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BLACK DEATH",
      "prompt": "During the bubonic plague of the 14th century, which…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "flea-ridden rodent helped spread disease?",
          "answer": "black rats"
        },
        {
          "question": "religious group was targeted by pogroms after false accusations of well-poisoning?",
          "answer": "Jews"
        },
        {
          "question": "kingdom lost its king Alfonso XI, and later unified with Aragon to form Spain?",
          "answer": "Castille"
        },
        {
          "question": "group of religious fanatics travelled around whipping themselves?",
          "answer": "Flagellants"
        },
        {
          "question": "French city was Pope Clement VI living in thanks to the \"Babylonian captivity\"?",
          "answer": "Avignon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian author described people fleeing from the plague in his Decameron?",
          "answer": "Giovanni Boccaccio"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king, succeeded by Richard II, passed the Statute of Labourers?",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian city, the home of the Doria family, was the destination of infected sailors from its port of Caffa?",
          "answer": "Genoa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POSTWAR EUROPEAN QUOTES",
      "prompt": "Who said...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“An Iron Curtain has descended across the Continent” in a speech delivered in Fulton, Missouri?",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "“The lady's not for turning” when refusing to slow her liberalization of Britain's economy?",
          "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "“We will bury you” to Western ambassadors?",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Soviet Union could not “improve thing without changing anything” in a party speech introducing his perestroika policy?",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Gaudet Mater Ecclesia” in his declaration opening Vatican II?",
          "answer": "John XXIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Non” in response to Great Britain joining the European Economic Community?",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "“This is our breakthrough” after his West Germany agreed to enter the European Coal and Steel Community?",
          "answer": "Konrad Adenauer"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Most of our people have never had it so good” while running for prime minister?",
          "answer": "Harold Macmillian"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "FRENCH AND INDIAN WAR",
      "prompt": "During the French and Indian War, who or what was the…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country which Britain acquired a large portion of as a result of the war?",
          "answer": "Canada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Young, then-British officer who surrendered Fort Necessity and later won at Trenton?",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the more general European conflict of which the war was a part?",
          "answer": "Seven Years War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battlefield outside Quebec where the war was decided?",
          "answer": "Plains of Abraham"
        },
        {
          "question": "British general who died commanding the decisive victory?",
          "answer": "James Wolfe"
        },
        {
          "question": "British-American painter who created a famous scene of that death?",
          "answer": "Benjamin West"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who died commanding the decisive loss?",
          "answer": "Louis de Montcalm"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe which began the war allied with the British but switched sides in 1758 after a rebellion led by Big Mortar and Moytoy?",
          "answer": "Cherokee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Otto Von Bismarck",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "country provoked into a war that led to the collapse of the Second Empire and the declaration of the Third Republic in Paris.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Emperor of Germany, under whom Bismarck served as Chancellor.",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "kingdom that Bismarck served before Germany’s founding.",
          "answer": "Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "two substances that will “solve the great questions of the day,” according to Bismarck.",
          "answer": "Blood and Iron or Eisen und Blut"
        },
        {
          "question": "religion targeted by Adalbert Falk’s May Laws.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "term for the anti-religious policies that included the May Laws.",
          "answer": "Kulturkampf"
        },
        {
          "question": "term used to describe Bismarck’s pragmatic diplomacy which focused on power balancing.",
          "answer": "Realpolitik"
        },
        {
          "question": "region ceded to Prussia and Austria in the Treaty of Vienna after a war with Denmark—",
          "answer": "Schleswig-Holstein"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The British Royal Navy",
      "prompt": "Name...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the appropriately-royal prefix to all of its ship names.",
          "answer": [
            "HMS",
            "Her and/or His Majesty’s Ship"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the victory over Napoleon’s fleet in Egypt’s Aboukir Bay, near a famous river.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Nile"
        },
        {
          "question": "the admiral who died at, but won, the Battle of Trafalgar.",
          "answer": "Horatio Nelson"
        },
        {
          "question": "that admiral’s flagship at Trafalgar, the navy’s oldest commissioned vessel.",
          "answer": "HMS Victory"
        },
        {
          "question": "the all-big-gun ship that sparked an early 20th century arms race.",
          "answer": "HMS Dreadnought"
        },
        {
          "question": "the flagship of Force H, whose 1941 sinking sparked a hunt for the Bismarck.",
          "answer": "HMS Hood"
        },
        {
          "question": "the war where the Sheffield was sunk.",
          "answer": "Falklands War"
        },
        {
          "question": "the 1922 treaty that limited the size of the Royal Navy, as well as those of four other countries, eight years prior to a similar treaty signed in London.",
          "answer": "Washington Naval Treaty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Dynastic Houses",
      "prompt": "Which ruling house or dynasty...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "ended when Elizabeth I died childless?",
          "answer": "House of Tudor"
        },
        {
          "question": "was overthrown by Vladimir Lenin?",
          "answer": "House of Romanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "ruled Austria until 1918 and included Maria Theresa?",
          "answer": [
            "House of Habsburg",
            "House of Hapsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was replaced by the House of Valois after over three centuries of ruling France?",
          "answer": "House of Capet or Capetian dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the current ruling house of England?",
          "answer": "House of Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "ruled Portugal for almost 200 years and included Prince Henry the Navigator?",
          "answer": "House of Aviz"
        },
        {
          "question": "included Gustavus Adolphus and names a Swedish warship that sank minutes into her maiden voyage?",
          "answer": "House of Vasa"
        },
        {
          "question": "ruled Poland, but ended after the death of Casimir the Great?",
          "answer": "Piast Dynasty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Congress of Vienna",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Alpine country whose neutrality was guaranteed.",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "country whose delegation was led by Tsar Alexander I.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesman who organized the Congress.",
          "answer": "Klemens Wenzel von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "French representative who forced his way into the inner circle and may have betrayed Napoleon’s conquests.",
          "answer": "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "French town, formerly home to a line of antipopes, which was not returned to the Papal States.",
          "answer": "Avignon"
        },
        {
          "question": "region home to Dresden, which was partially given to Prussia.",
          "answer": "Saxony"
        },
        {
          "question": "second wife of Napoleon who was made Duchess of Parma.",
          "answer": "Marie-Louise"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swedish territory on the south Baltic coast, given from Denmark to Prussia.",
          "answer": "Swedish Pomerania"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The French Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "dynasty that was overthrown.",
          "answer": "Bourbon Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "fortress and prison that was stormed on July 14, 1789.",
          "answer": "Bastille Saint-Antoine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jacobin politician and member of the Committee of Public Safety who was guillotined in the Thermidorian Reaction.",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "period of mass political executions led by that man, which was ended by the Thermidorian Reaction.",
          "answer": "Reign of Terror"
        },
        {
          "question": "vow by representatives of the Third Estate to not disperse until a constitution was written.",
          "answer": [
            "Tennis Court Oath",
            "Serment de Jeu de Paume"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "government overthrown by Napoleon in the coup of 18 Brumaire.",
          "answer": "Directory"
        },
        {
          "question": "town where the royal family was recognized while attempting to flee to Austria.",
          "answer": "Varennes"
        },
        {
          "question": "public field where the National Guard massacred anti-royal protesters in 1791.",
          "answer": "Champ de Mars Massacre"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Otto von Bismarck",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire he created after a victory over France, uniting the former states of the Holy Roman Empire.",
          "answer": [
            "Germany",
            "German Empire",
            "German Reich"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First Kaiser of that empire, who Bismarck served for decades.",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion he targeted in the kulturkampf, as he favored the Protestant majority.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "The pair of militaristic concepts that Bismarck claimed would “resolve” the “great questions of the time.”",
          "answer": [
            "blood and iron",
            "in either order",
            "prompt if only one is given"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The country to the north that he invaded in 1864 for the territory of Schleswig-Holstein.",
          "answer": "Denmark"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conference he organized to regulate the Scramble for Africa.",
          "answer": "Congress of Berlin or Berlin Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "ForeignpolicythatBismarckchampioned,respondingtothegivencircumstancesratherthanfollowing ideology.",
          "answer": "realpolitik"
        },
        {
          "question": "Duchy seized with Schleswig and Holstein in 1864, of which Bismarck was made a Duke at the end of his career.",
          "answer": "Lauenberg"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Napoleonic Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that Napoleon ruled as Emperor.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that successfully drove out Napoleon after he captured Moscow.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Main waterway of western Germany, a river that named a confederation of German states created by Napoleon.",
          "answer": "Rhine River or the Confederation of the Rhine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where he decisively defeated the Ottomans at the Battle of the Pyramids.",
          "answer": "Ottoman Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive force assembled by Napoleon to invade Britain, but which never did; it formed the core of Napoleon’s invasion force in Russia.",
          "answer": "Grande Arm´ee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal family restored to power under Louis XVIII [eighteenth] after the Napoleonic Wars.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign isolationist policy developed by Napoleon, forbidding allies from trading with Britain.",
          "answer": "Continental System"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive victory for Napoleon against the Third Coalition, after which he signed the Treaty of Pressburg.",
          "answer": "Battle of Austerlitz or the Battle of the Three Emperors"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Operation Barbarossa",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Former country that Nazi Germany targeted in Barbarossa, on the Eastern Front in Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union or USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance of Germany and Italy that launched the invasion.",
          "answer": "Axis Powers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Nazi Germany that ordered it.",
          "answer": "Adolf Hitler"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genocide of six million people that took place in occupied territories after the invasion.",
          "answer": "Holocaust"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-aggression pact that Germany broke to launch Barbarossa.",
          "answer": "Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Target of Army Group North during the invasion. The siege of this city lasted 872 days.",
          "answer": [
            "Leningrad",
            "St. Petersburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "casus belli of the invasion, a German word that translates as “living space.”",
          "answer": "Lebensraum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Code name for the summer 1942 offensive of Army Group South in the Caucasus, briefly capturing Soviet oil fields.",
          "answer": [
            "Case Blue or Fall Blau",
            "Operation Braunschweig"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Charles de Gaulle",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Elected position he held as leader of the Fifth Republic, unlike the appointed Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "President"
        },
        {
          "question": "Puppet government that opposed him, set up by Nazi Germany to administer southern France.",
          "answer": "Vichy France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vehicles that he commanded during World War II. German vehicles of this type were known as panzers.",
          "answer": "tanks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Soviet military alliance that de Gaulle partially withdrew from in 1966.",
          "answer": "North Atlantic Treaty Organizaiton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bloody World War I battle in which he was taken prisoner while Marshal Petain commanded French forces.",
          "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
        },
        {
          "question": "French colony that won its independence in the E´vian Accords during de Gaulle’s leadership of the Fifth Republic.",
          "answer": "French Algeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military operations he authorized in the Sahara Desert, which France also carried out above Pacific atolls.",
          "answer": "nuclear tests"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War II conference where he met with Roosevelt and Churchill and agreed to force an “unconditional surrender.”",
          "answer": "Casablanca Conference"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Spanish Armada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the Armada was launched.",
          "answer": [
            "1500s",
            "16th century",
            "1588"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Spain who launched the Armada.",
          "answer": "Philip II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Queen whose Tilbury Speech rallied the waiting English army.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "North Atlantic water current that pushed the defeated, escaping Armada into the coasts of Scotland and Ireland.",
          "answer": "Gulf Stream"
        },
        {
          "question": "French port city across the Channel from Dover where the Armada waited, in crescent formation, for Parma’s army to board.",
          "answer": "Calais"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of warship, including “hellburners,” which the English used to scatter that crescent formation.",
          "answer": [
            "fireship",
            "any description of a ship set on fire and/or used as a bomb"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish Duke who was commander-in-chief of the Armada.",
          "answer": [
            "Alonso P´erez de Guzm´an y de Zu´n˜iga-Sotomayor, Duke of Medina Sidonia",
            "any underlined part",
            "do not prompt if “Medina”",
            "“Sidonia” is given alone"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Flemish port town where an indecisive battle cost the Armada just five ships, but prevented it from picking up Parma’s army.",
          "answer": "Battle of Gravelines"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Sri Lanka",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European power that occupied it in 1640, ruling it in an extensive colonial empire from Amsterdam.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of the Seven United Netherlands or the Netherlands",
            "Dutch Republic",
            "Republic of the Seven United Provinces"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European power that discovered it and built a fort at Colombo. Its explorers included Vasco da Gama.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion followed by the majority of its residents, primarily the Theravada sect.",
          "answer": "Buddhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cash crop introduced in the 19th century by the British, produce into black and green drinks.",
          "answer": "tea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group on Sri Lanka that formed a Tiger resistance movement against the majority Sinhalese.",
          "answer": [
            "Tamil",
            "Tamil Tigers and other elaborations"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to the island while under colonial rule.",
          "answer": "Ceylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native kingdom that resisted European occupation until the British conquest. It began as an ally of the Kingdom of Kotte.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Kandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian dynasty that occupied Sri Lanka under Rajendra. They dominated the Indian Ocean stretching all the way to the Malay Peninsula.",
          "answer": "Chola dynasty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hundred Years’ War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country ruled by the Plantagenets that fought France in the war.",
          "answer": "England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling house of the French during the war. It succeeded the House of Capet in 1328.",
          "answer": "House of Valois , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "French peasant girl who helped relieve Orleans and was later burned at the stake.",
          "answer": "Joan of Arc or Jeanne d’Arc"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Charles VII was crowned King of France in 1429, with the help of the aforementioned peasant girl.",
          "answer": "Reims , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Epidemic disease that struck Europe, weakening France before the Battle of Poitiers [pwa-tee-ay].",
          "answer": [
            "Black Death",
            "bubonic plague",
            "black plague"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1346 battle, fought ten years before Poitiers, where English longbowmen first saw success.",
          "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
        },
        {
          "question": "City on the English Channel that was taken by the English after that battle.",
          "answer": "Calais"
        },
        {
          "question": "1340 naval battle fought in the Netherlands, giving England brief control of the sea.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sluys"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "17th Century England",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Virgin Queen” of England who died in 1603, ending the House of Tudor.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of disaster that destroyed St. Paul’s Cathedral and thousands of houses in London in 1666.",
          "answer": "Great Fire of London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Architect who re-designed St. Paul’s and dozens of other churches after that disaster.",
          "answer": "Sir Christopher Wren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Street where that disaster began in a bakery.",
          "answer": "Pudding Lane"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who recorded his account of that disaster, and an earlier plague, in a famous diary.",
          "answer": "Samuel Pepys , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group that, according to Titus Oates, supposedly planned the Popish Plot to assassinate the king in 1678.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Catholics",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King of England overthrown by William and Mary in the 1688 Glorious Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "James II of England",
            "James VII of Scotland, but do not"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Acts that required public employees to be members of the Church of England, opposed by that king.",
          "answer": "Test Acts"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Guns",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American lobby group that advocates for gun rights, once led by actor Charlton Heston.",
          "answer": "National Rifle Association or NRA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet rifle favored by guerilla groups, the first of the Kalashnikov family.",
          "answer": [
            "AK-47",
            "Automat Kalashnikov 47"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese dynasty that invented gunpowder and fell to the Yuan.",
          "answer": "Song Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gun company, founded by Samuel, that popularized the 45-caliber revolver.",
          "answer": "Colt Manufacturing Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that used the Maxim gun to conquer Sudan at Omdurman, avenging the death of “Chinese” Gordon.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Daimyo, an ally of Tokugawa Ieyasu and Toyotomi Hideyoshi, who used arquebuses to win the Battle of Nagashino.",
          "answer": "Oda Nobunaga"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gun company whose rifle was the “Gun that Won the West” and whose family built a “Mystery House” in California.",
          "answer": [
            "Winchester Repeating Arms Company",
            "Winchester Mystery House"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "16th century Spanish formation, known as the “third,” that heavily featured musketeers.",
          "answer": "tercio"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Divided Germany",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that occupied East Germany during World War II under Joseph Stalin.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "USSR",
            "CCCP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Barrier that divided Germany’s capital city starting in 1961.",
          "answer": "Berlin Wall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied method of supplying that city for 15 months in the late 1940s.",
          "answer": [
            "Berlin airlift",
            "descriptions of airdropping supplies, flying supplies in, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1945 conference in Germany where the allies divided their control of West Germany.",
          "answer": "Potsdam Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that served as West Germany’s capital and base of government, while its lawful capital was divided in the East.",
          "answer": "Bonn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity that spiked in price in a namesake 1977 crisis, after which it was imported from Vietnam instead of Brazil.",
          "answer": "coffee crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "West German chancellor and advocate of Ostpolitik who resigned after his aide, Gunter Guillaume, was revealed to be an East German spy.",
          "answer": "Willy Brandt"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German leader who implemented the New Economic System and was succeeded by Erich Honecker in the early 1970s.",
          "answer": "Walter Ulbricht"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Russian Vocabulary",
      "prompt": "Give the Russian term for...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The main government complex in Moscow, as well as a type of fortress in general.",
          "answer": "Kremlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "ThefactionthatsplitfromtheMensheviksintheRussianRevolution,fromtheRussianfor“majority.”",
          "answer": "Bolsheviks"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Restructuring,” that paired with “glasnost” as a means of reform in the late Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "perestroika"
        },
        {
          "question": "A Soviet prison labor camp, derived from an acronym for the system.",
          "answer": "gulag"
        },
        {
          "question": "A former newspaper of the Communist Party whose name translates to “Truth.”",
          "answer": "Pravda"
        },
        {
          "question": "Damaging material used to blackmail political opponents.",
          "answer": "kompromat"
        },
        {
          "question": "The loyal police force of Ivan the Terrible, who killed thousands in Novgorod.",
          "answer": [
            "Oprichniki",
            "Oprichnina",
            "Oprichniks"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "A seasonal second cottage in the countryside, gifted to party officials in the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "dacha"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "English Edwards",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country north of England that gave Edward I his nickname and whose army was later led by William Wallace.",
          "answer": "Scotland"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king who fathered Edward VI with Jane Seymour, one of his six wives.",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "London church where Edward II knighted over 200 men in the Feast of the Swans, and where all English monarchs have been crowned since 1066.",
          "answer": [
            "Westminster Abbey",
            "Collegiate Church of St. Peter at Westminster"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern ruling house of England whose first monarch was Edward VII.",
          "answer": "House of Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "English prince who won at Crecy and Poitiers [pwa-tee-ay] during the Hundred Years’ War.",
          "answer": "Edward the Black Prince or Edward of Woodstock"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who imprisoned princes Edward V and Richard of Shrewsbury in the Tower of London in 1483.",
          "answer": "Richard III"
        },
        {
          "question": "American woman for whose love Edward VIII [8] abdicated the throne.",
          "answer": [
            "Wallis Simpson",
            "Wallis Spencer",
            "Bessie Wallis Warfield"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English nobleman who was defeated by the future Edward I at Evesham after he overthrew Henry III.",
          "answer": "Simon de Montfort"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Scramble for Africa",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "German capital city where an 1884 conference attempted to organize the Scramble.",
          "answer": "Berlin Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "German chancellor who proposed that 1884 conference.",
          "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African empire that fought the battles of Rorke’s Drift, Ulundi, and Isandlwana against the British.",
          "answer": [
            "Zulu Empire",
            "Zululand",
            "amaZulu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern African country that defeated Italy at Adowa to win its independence.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "US protectorate country on the Atlantic coast that remained independent during the Scramble.",
          "answer": "Liberia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Belgian king who personally owned the Congo Free State.",
          "answer": "Leopold II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose “Pink Map” proposed a linking of its African colonies.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "1898 incident that nearly led to war in Southern Sudan between Britain and France.",
          "answer": "Fashoda Crisis Incident, etc."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Treaty of Versailles",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French city whose 1919 Peace Conference negotiated much of its terms.",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President at the time of signing.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Prime Minister who helped negotiate it.",
          "answer": "David Lloyd George"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian “Premier of Victory” who signed it.",
          "answer": "Vittorio Orlando"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial clause, listed as Article 231, that allowed countries to demand German reparations.",
          "answer": [
            "War Guilt Clause",
            "Article 231 if somehow given before mentioned"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British economist who grimly predicted the Economic Consequences of the treaty.",
          "answer": "John Maynard Keynes , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Province given to Japan that sparked the May Fourth Movement.",
          "answer": "Shandong"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Senators, including George Norris and Hiram Johnson, that strongly opposed ratification.",
          "answer": "Irreconcilables"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French King beheaded in 1793 along with his wife, Marie Antoinette.",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prison that was stormed in 1789, marking the beginning of the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "Bastille Saint-Antoine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who was executed in July 1794 after growing the Committee of Public Safety during the Reign of Terror.",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "French aristocrat and officer who fought in the American Revolution before joining in the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "Marquis de Lafayette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vow taken by members of the Third Estate in 1789, formally establishing their opposition to the ruling monarch.",
          "answer": "Tennis Court Oath"
        },
        {
          "question": "French finance minister whose dismissal from the service of the king incited a major rebellion in 1789.",
          "answer": "Jacques Necker"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary figure executed for the assassination of Jacobin leader Jean-Paul Marat.",
          "answer": "Charlotte Corday"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Joseph Stalin",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Predecessor to Stalin as leader of the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin or Vladimir Ulyanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian revolutionary whom Stalin exiled and had killed in Mexico in 1940.",
          "answer": "Leon Trotsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "1945 conference, held in the Crimea, of the leaders of the US, UK, and USSR to discuss a post-World War II peace plan.",
          "answer": "Yalta Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern country where Stalin killed millions of people in a famine known as Holodomor in the 1930s.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of centralized economic development plans developed by Stalin which continued after his death until 1991.",
          "answer": "Five-Year Plans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police service under Stalin, responsible for carrying out executing Stalin’s mass purges; it preceded the KGB.",
          "answer": [
            "NKVD",
            "People’s Commissariat for Internal Affairs",
            "Narodnyy Komissariat Vnutrennikh Del"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaign organized by Stalin shortly before his death to arrest Jews of a certain profession, based on the false belief that they were conspiring against Soviet leadership.",
          "answer": "Doctors’ Plot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Successor to Stalin who only held his position for two years, before being replaced by Nikita Khrushchev.",
          "answer": "Georgy Malenkov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Irish War of Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which Ireland sought its independence.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "Great Britain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city used by the Irish Republic, the Irish Free State, and modern Ireland.",
          "answer": "Dublin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday that names a 1916 Rising led by Patrick Pearse.",
          "answer": "Easter Rising"
        },
        {
          "question": "Day of the week nicknamed “Bloody” after a 1920 massacre at a Gaelic Football game.",
          "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Prime Minister who led Britain during the War and represented Britain at the Paris Peace Conference.",
          "answer": "David Lloyd George"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paramilitary force nicknamed for the color of their uniforms, composed primarily of World War I veterans.",
          "answer": [
            "Black and Tans",
            "Royal Irish Constabulary Special Reserve"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Left-wing political party that declared the breakaway Dail Eireann in 1919, starting the War of Independence.",
          "answer": "Sinn Fein , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of that political party, who chaired the Irish delegation at treaty talks in 1921.",
          "answer": "Arthur Griffith"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "France in World War I",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French capital city and namesake of a German siege gun that weighed half a million pounds.",
          "answer": "Paris Gun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the two countries allied in the Triple Entente with France.",
          "answer": [
            "Russia and/or United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French city where the treaty ending World War I was signed.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "French Prime Minister at the end of the war, known as “The Tiger.”",
          "answer": "Georges Clemenceau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Forest on the northern border of France that the Germans pushed through in August 1914.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Ardennes Forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "September 1914 battle, a “miracle” for the French that turned the German advance into a stalemate.",
          "answer": "First Battle of the Marne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest battle of the war, fought in 1916 over the Meuse Heights.",
          "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Allied Commander of the French forces who criticized the peace as an “armistice for 20 years” because it was too lenient.",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Foch"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Concert of Europe",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Iron Chancellor” of Prussia who recreated the system.",
          "answer": [
            "Otto von Bismarck",
            "Otto Eduard Leopold"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German city where that chancellor held an 1878 congress to address the Balkans.",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian city that names the original version of the Concert, created following the Napoleonic wars.",
          "answer": "Vienna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year, called the Spring of Nations, in which dozens of revolutions led to the collapse of the first Concert of Europe.",
          "answer": "1848"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian diplomat who organized the Concert of Europe in 1815.",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that hosted an 1818 congress, eighty years after hosting the peace talks that ended the War of Austrian Succession.",
          "answer": [
            "Aix-la-Chapelle",
            "Aachen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance organized by Alexander I that united the monarchist powers of Russia, Prussia, and Austria.",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Alliance",
            "Grand Alliance"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British diplomat who brokered the 1814 Treaty of Chaumont, then pursued non-intervention on the continent.",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh",
            "Lord Castlereagh"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial Flordia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European power that colonized Florida and ruled it from Madrid.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "English colony founded by James Oglethorpe that provided a buffer between Florida and the rest of the 13 colonies.",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer of Florida who searched for the Fountain of Youth.",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Florida city founded in 1565, the oldest continuously inhabited European city in the US.",
          "answer": "Saint Augustine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American tribe that fought a war against Andrew Jackson.",
          "answer": "Seminoles"
        },
        {
          "question": "1819 agreement in which James Monroe’s Secretary of State secured Florida for the United States.",
          "answer": [
            "Adams-Onis Treaty",
            "Transcontinental Treaty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City for which the Spanish traded Florida after it was seized in the Seven Years’ War.",
          "answer": "Havana"
        },
        {
          "question": "1832 treaty that forced the aforementioned tribe out of Florida following the Indian Removal Act.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Payne’s Landing"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Muslims in Spain",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Catholic Monarchs, of Castille and Aragon, who persecuted Muslims.",
          "answer": [
            "Ferdinand and Isabella",
            "Ferdinand II of Aragon and Isabella I of Castille"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Strait crossed by Muslim forces who invaded from Morocco.",
          "answer": "Strait of Gibraltar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribunal, established in 1478, that persecuted hundreds of thousands of non-Christians in Spain.",
          "answer": "Spanish Inquisition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caliphate that seized control of Hispania in 711.",
          "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "800-year-long period that ended in 1492 when Spain defeated the last Muslim kingdom on the Iberian Peninsula.",
          "answer": "Reconquista"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Muslim kingdom to fall to the Spanish, an emirate on the southern shores of Spain.",
          "answer": "Granada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Roman fort that was made into that kingdom’s royal palace by Yusuf I in 1333.",
          "answer": "Alhambra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last dynastic house to fall to Spain; it was led by Boabdil.",
          "answer": "Nasrid dynasty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Recent British Prime Ministers",
      "prompt": "For the purposes of this lightning round, recent means since 1900. Name the British Prime Minister who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Gave the “we shall fight on the beaches” speech in May 1940 during his first month as PM.",
          "answer": "Sir Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known as the “Iron Lady” and passed away in 2013.",
          "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned as PM after the success of the Brexit referendum in 2016.",
          "answer": "David Cameron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proclaimed “Peace in our time” after signing the Munich Agreement with Hitler.",
          "answer": "Neville Chamberlain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed the “People’s Budget” and represented Britain at Versailles in 1919.",
          "answer": "David Lloyd George"
        },
        {
          "question": "Replaced John Major in a victory for “New Labour.”",
          "answer": "Tony Blair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave the “Wind of Change” speech in 1960, giving tacit approval to African independence movements.",
          "answer": "Harold Macmillan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was embarrassed by the publishing of the Zinoviev letter, after which his party lost an election to Stanley Baldwin’s party.",
          "answer": "Ramsay MacDonald"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Serfdom",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "System under which serfdom flourished involving landowners exchanging use of their land for peasant labor.",
          "answer": "Feudalism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last European empire to outlaw serfdom, done so by Tsar Alexander II.",
          "answer": "Russian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Thinker who stated both serfdom and free labor are equally primitive in Das Kapital.",
          "answer": "Karl Marx"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th century “Revolt” led by Wat Tyler which effectively ended serfdom in England.",
          "answer": [
            "Peasants' Revolt",
            "the Great Rising,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "People of the steppe who united with serfs in Pugachev's Rebellion which captured the city of Kazan.",
          "answer": "Cossacks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medieval tenant farmers with great autonomy who were legally bound to a manor.",
          "answer": [
            "Villein",
            "Cotter,",
            "Crofter"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for serfs or slaves in Viking societies, often used as a punishment for a failure to repay debts.",
          "answer": "Thralls"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economist who claimed collectivist policies led to destitution in The Road to Serfdom.",
          "answer": "Friedrich August von Hayek 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Equatorial Africa (AEF)",
      "prompt": "Concerning French Equatorial Africa, also called AEF, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Desert that covered most of the northern parts of the AEF.",
          "answer": "Sahara Desert"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion of pre-colonial rulers who destroyed the mune and took a pilgrimage to Mecca.",
          "answer": [
            "Islam",
            "Muslim"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Government-in-exile led by Charles de Gaulle, joined by the AEF in opposition to the Vichy regime.",
          "answer": [
            "Free France",
            "Free French forces"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Republic of the Congo capital that held a Conference to increase colonial rights for natives.",
          "answer": "Brazzaville"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country David Dacko and Jean-Bédel Bokassa governed from Bangui.",
          "answer": "Central African Republic or CAR"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constituent country that Félix Malloum and Hissene Habré led.",
          "answer": "Republic of Chad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strip of land that Libya tried to take in the Toyota War.",
          "answer": "Aouzou Strip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Black French administrator, earlier governor of Guadeloupe, who had his ashes placed in the Panthéon.",
          "answer": "Félix Éboué 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Portuguese-English Relations",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Portugal, a vital Red Cross base for the Allies in World War Two.",
          "answer": "Lisbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "City once known as Bombay, given as a dowry to England by Portugal.",
          "answer": "Mumbai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty between John I and Philippa of Lancaster, sharing its name with the House of Queen Elizabeth II.",
          "answer": "Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Portugal allied with England after the Battle of Blenheim.",
          "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese Dynasty of Charles II's wife, founded by John I.",
          "answer": "Braganza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that guaranteed both nations would not tax wines and textiles.",
          "answer": "Methuen Treaty"
        },
        {
          "question": "War England helped to bring back Portuguese self-rule from Spain.",
          "answer": [
            "Restoration War",
            "Acclamation War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Map of Portugal's African claims that forced the 1890 British Ultimatum.",
          "answer": "Rose-coloured Map or Pink Map 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the rise of Nazism, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the rise of nazism, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Austrian figure who assumed leadership of the Nazis over Anton Drexler.",
          "answer": "Adolf Hitler"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hero of World War One and German president who surrendered many of his powers to the rising Nazi party.",
          "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite paramilitary unit led by Heinrich Himmler whose name translates to \"Defense Echelon.\"",
          "answer": "SS or Schutzstaffel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Manifesto written by a Nazi leader while in jail which outlined his plans to form a Greater German Reich.",
          "answer": "Mein Kampf ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "1923 \"Putsch\" in Munich which aimed to overthrow the sitting government.",
          "answer": "Beer Hall Putsch"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War One flying ace and creator of the Gestapo [[geh-SHTAH-poh]] who also developed the \"Four-year Plan.\"",
          "answer": "Hermann Göring ] or Hermann Wilhelm Göring"
        },
        {
          "question": "Openly gay leader of the SA who was purged from the Nazi party following the Night of the Long Knives.",
          "answer": "Ernst Röhm ] or Ernst Julius Günther Röhm"
        },
        {
          "question": "1933 Act which facilitated the Machtergreifung [[mahk-tehr-GRY-foong]], or the Nazi seizure of power, by making Germany a one-party state.",
          "answer": "Enabling Act or Ermächtigungsgesetz 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Congress of Vienna",
      "prompt": "Name the the congress of vienna...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French Emperor whose deposition and exile led to the convening of the Congress of Vienna.",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "either underlined portion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation, known as the Helvetic Republic under Napoleonic rule, whose 22 cantons had their perpetual neutrality guaranteed.",
          "answer": [
            "Switzerland",
            "Swiss Confederation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom tied to the Russian throne which was formerly known as the Duchy of Warsaw.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Poland or Królestwo Polskie",
            "Congress Poland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesman who organized the Congress of Vienna.",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tsar of Russia who seized the Grand Duchy of Finland for himself at the congress.",
          "answer": "Alexander I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomat and perpetual turncoat who represented France at the Congress.",
          "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "French military commander who was allowed to retain his role as regent of Sweden, eventually becoming its king.",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Baptiste Bernadotte",
            "Charles XIV [[the fourteenth John"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island kingdom that unified with Savoy and regained its mainland territories in the Congress.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Sardinia 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3 African Decolonization"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Treaty of Versailles",
      "prompt": "During the signing of the Treaty of Versailles, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War the treaty officially ended.",
          "answer": "World War One or the First World War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation once led by Wilhelm [[VIHL-helm]] II that signed the treaty with the Allies.",
          "answer": [
            "Germany",
            "German Empire",
            "Weimar Germany"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Intergovernmental body and predecessor to the United Nations which was created at Versailles.",
          "answer": [
            "League of Nations",
            "Société des Nations"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president who attended the Treaty of Versailles, forming the Big Three with David Lloyd George and Georges Clemenceau [[cleh-mehn-SOH]].",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson or Thomas Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Earlier treaty signed by Germany with Soviet Russia, overturned at Versailles.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Brest-Litovsk"
        },
        {
          "question": "International free city set up next to the Polish Corridor.",
          "answer": "Danzig or Gdańsk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that received the port of Qingdao [[CHING-DOW]] in the treaty, triggering the May 4th Movement in another country.",
          "answer": "Empire of Japan or Nippon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region of western Germany separated by the treaty and made a League of Nations mandate until 1935.",
          "answer": "Saarland 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 4"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding what some call the \"first global war\", name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about Regarding what some call the \"first global war\", name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the Seven Years' War occurred.",
          "answer": [
            "18th Century",
            "1700s"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English name for the North American theater of the Seven Years' War.",
          "answer": "French and Indian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty which ended the Seven Years' War which shares its name with the treaty which ended the Revolutionary War.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Paris",
            "Treaty of 1763"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City near the Plains of Abraham, where both James Wolfe and Louis Montcalm died.",
          "answer": "Quebec City or Ville de Québec"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Elder\" British prime minister credited for most of the victories during the Annus Mirabilis [[meer-AH-bih-liss]].",
          "answer": "William Pitt the Elder"
        },
        {
          "question": "Victorious general at Plassey who, with Warren Hastings, established British hegemony [[heh-JEH-moh-nee]] in India.",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Clive",
            "Clive of India"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City at the center of the French East India Company seized by the British in 1761.",
          "answer": [
            "Pondicherry",
            "Puducherry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Naval victory near St. Nazaire where the Comte de Conflans [[KOHMT duh cohn- FLAHN]] lost to Edward Hawke's fleet near the Bay of Biscay.",
          "answer": "Battle of Quiberon ] Bay 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "England marches to war! Name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about England marches to war! Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "King whose conquest of England in 1066 is depicted in the Bayeaux [[\"Bayou\"]] Tapestry.",
          "answer": [
            "William the Conqueror or William I",
            "William the Bastard"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Six-wived King of England who defeated the French at the Battle of the Spurs.",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Great\" King of Wessex who defeated the Great Heathen Army at Edington.",
          "answer": "Alfred the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Hammer of the Scots\" who defeated William Wallace at Falkirk.",
          "answer": [
            "Edward I",
            "Edward Longshanks"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King whose longbowmen devestated the French at Agincourt [[ah-jin-KOHR]].",
          "answer": "Henry V"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of the \"Black Prince\" who dealt with the Plague and the early phases of the Hundred Years War.",
          "answer": "Edward III or Edward of Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Denmark who deposed Aethelred the Unready to take the throne of England.",
          "answer": [
            "Sweyn ] Forkbeard or Sveinn Haraldsson tjúguskegg",
            "be lenient on pronunciation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of Isabella of Angoulême [[ahn-goo-LEHM]] taken prisoner after the Battle of Lewes [[LOOS]] during the Second Barons' War.",
          "answer": "Henry III or Henry of Winchester 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This European power used the \"ten-cow rule\" to distinguish and privilege some colonial subjects. The Casement Report criticized the colonial policies of this European power, alleging that it cut the (20 pts)",
        "hands off unproductive rubber workers. This European power treated the Tutsis better than the Hutus in what became Rwanda, and ran a so-called (10 pts)",
        "\"Free State\" exploited by King Leopold II. For 10 points, name this European country which colonized most of the Congo."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Belgium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Mehmet Ali Ağca attempted to assassinate someone holding this position. Eugenio Pacelli\nwas criticized for his silence over the Holocaust while he held it. One of these people\ncondemned (20 pts) ",
        "contraception in Humanae Vitae. Karol Wojtyla was the first non- (10 pts) ",
        "Italian\nto hold this position in over 400 years, and Jorge Bergoglio became the first non-European in\nover 1,000 years when he succeeded Benedict XVI. For 10 points, name this head of the Roman\nCatholic Church."
      ],
      "answer": "Pope"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person was the subject of a \"nullification trial\" convened by Calixtus III. This\nperson led troops that captured John Talbot at the Battle of Patay. After getting an\naudience with (20 pts) ",
        "Charles VII, this person correctly identified the disguised king. This hero\nof the Siege of (10 pts) ",
        "Orleans claimed to have visions of St. Michael and St. Margaret. For 10\npoints, name this woman who was burned at the stake after fighting for the French in the\nHundred Year's War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jon of Arc",
        "Joan Arc",
        "Jeanne d'Arc",
        "Jeanne Arc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man commissioned a battle flag with a motto sewn on it that he attributed to James\nLawrence, \"Don't Give Up the Ship.\" This man opposed Jesse Elliot, the captain of the\nNiagara, at (20 pts) ",
        "Put-In Bay. He issued the message \"We have (10 pts) ",
        "met the enemy and they are\nours\" to his commander in the field, William Henry Harrison. For 10 points, name this naval\ncommander who defeated the British at the Battle of Lake Erie during the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Hazard Perry",
        "Perry"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Along with “liberty,” this good names the Russian revolutionary group that split into the People’s Will and Black Repartition. Economist Henry George proposed a single tax on this good and the abolition of all other taxes in his book (20 pts)",
        "Progress and Poverty. The 18th- century French economic school known as (10 pts)",
        "Physiocracy argued that wealth was entirely derived from development of this good. For 10 points, name this good necessary for farming."
      ],
      "answer": "land"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was encouraged to develop his alcoholism by the harsh General Sutgof (SOOT- goff), who commanded the Cadet School where he won an appointment to the Preobrazhensky (pree-AH-bruh-ZEN-skee) Regiment of the Imperial Guard. He was criticized by his mentor (20 pts)",
        "Mily Balakirev (buh-LAH-kee-rev) for his tone poem about a (10 pts)",
        "witches' sabbath, Night on Bald Mountain. For 10 points, name this Russian composer of Pictures at an Exhibition."
      ],
      "answer": "Modest Mussorgsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This king launched an invasion of the Netherlands to claim the inheritance of his wife Maria Theresa of Spain. As a child, his chambers were invaded by an angry mob during the civil war known as the Fronde. As king, this man revoked the Edict of (20 pts)",
        "Nantes and sparked the War of the Spanish Succession by proclaiming his grandson (10 pts)",
        "Philip V king of Spain. For 10 points, name this King of France who created the palace of Versailles and who was known as “The Sun King.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Antonio Canova sculpted this man as Mars the Peacemaker, and he was painted by Antoine-Jean Gros Visiting the Plague Victims of Jaffa. This man’s military accomplishments are celebrated with the (20 pts)",
        "Vendome Column, and in an Ingres [ANG-gruh] painting that shows this man wearing a gold wreath and holding the scepter of Charlemagne while seated on his (10 pts)",
        "Imperial Throne. A painting of this man by Jacques-Louis David shows him perched on a rearing horse while Crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French emperor who was defeated at Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This institution, led by August von Galen, opposed the Action T4 euthanasia program. Eugenio Pacelli was the chief negotiator for one treaty that led to recognition of this entity. The Centre Party supported this entity during (20 pts)",
        "Bismarck’s time as Chancellor. The document Mit brennender Sorge condemned attacks on this institution by (10 pts)",
        "Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this institution officially recognized by Nazi Germany after the Reichskonkordat, often criticized for not doing enough to stop the Holocaust under its leader, Pope Pius XII."
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader, who with George Smythe co-founded the Young England group, was criticized by one politician about the Bulgarian Horrors in the (20 pts)",
        "Midlothian Campaign. This man represented the British delegation during the Congress of Berlin and used money from the Rothschild family to purchase shares for the Suez Canal. This leader gave the title Empress of (10 pts)",
        "India to Queen Victoria, who made him the First Earl of Beaconsfield. For ten points, name this 19th century Conservative Jewish Prime Minister who was the rival of William Gladstone."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s government was defeated by a promise to create a universal National Health Service under Labour Party leader Clement (20 pts)",
        "Attlee, whom this man suggested would need “a Gestapo” to implement his plans. This man proclaimed “I have nothing to offer but blood, (10 pts)",
        "toil, tears, and sweat” upon taking office in 1940, shortly before Germany began “the Blitz” against his country. For ten points, name this British Prime Minister during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s ministry saw the passage of the Railways act, which was introduced by this man’s minister of transport, Eric Geddes. This man won the “Coupon election” against Andrew Bonar (20 pts)",
        "Law, and avoided war with Turkey after an invasion of the Dardanelles in the Chanak Crisis. While Minister of the Exchequer under Herbert Asquith, this man championed the (10 pts)",
        "People’s Budget, and this man’s ministry saw women gain the right to vote in Great Britain. For ten points, name this Welsh British prime minister of the Liberal party who led Great Britain at the Versailles Conference."
      ],
      "answer": "David Lloyd George"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wolfgang Capito and Martin Bucer invited this man to minister to French refugees in Strasbourg. At the Synod of Dort, the Arminians broke with this man’s followers. This predecessor of Theodore Beza ordered Michael (20 pts)",
        "Servetus burned at the stake for heresy. His faith is often summarized in “five points,” including limited atonement and total depravity, which were first laid out in his (10 pts)",
        "Institutes of the Christian Religion. For ten points, name this Protestant theologian who took power in Geneva, Switzerland, and whose followers believe in predestination."
      ],
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Warning: two answers required. One of these two countries was aided by the New Model Army against the other country at the Battle of the Dunes. The Duc d’Enghein switched sides to command the army of one of these countries, which he had earlier defeated at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Rocroi in the service of the other. One of these countries tried to place Phillip of Anjou on the throne of the other after the death of (10 pts)",
        "Charles II, resulting in a Bourbon alliance. For ten points, the Treaty of the Pyrenees was signed by what two countries, one of whose namesake succession war was started by the other’s Louis XIV."
      ],
      "answer": "France and Spain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A friend of this man was beheaded when they attempted to flee his country, possibly to defect to George II of Britain. This monarch created an alliance of German princes called the Furstenbund and oversaw the First (20 pts)",
        "Partition of Poland. The death of Empress Elisabeth led this ruler to sign a peace treaty with Peter the Great in a conflict where his army won at Rossbach, which he began by invading Saxony. His Anti-Machiavel influenced (10 pts)",
        "Voltaire to correspond with this monarch who also invited J.S. Bach to Potsdam. For ten points, name this leader of Prussia during the Seven Years War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Frederick II of Prussia Frederick the Great",
        "Frederick IV of Brandenburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man dissolved parliament after Franz von Papen lost heavily in a vote of no confidence. After Marinus van der Lubbe was caught attempting to set (20 pts)",
        "fire to government buildings, this leader suspended civil liberties in the Reichstag fire decrees. This man rose to fame after working with Erich (10 pts)",
        "Ludendorff to orchestrate a victory at Tannenberg. For ten points, name this final president of Weimar Germany, a politician who appointed Adolf Hitler chancellor well after being honored as the namesake of a zeppelin."
      ],
      "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group operated the Peterhof base in Novgorod until they were expelled by Ivan III. This group’s defeat of Valdemar IV led to the Treaty of Stralsund, which guaranteed this organization’s control of (20 pts)",
        "Visby. It established trade posts in important cities called kontors, and its members were governed by the Laws of (10 pts)",
        "Lu¨beck, named for its most important town. This organization began as a group of free Imperial cities seeking to control the Baltic fish trade. For ten points, name this medieval trade league in northern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Hanseatic League or the Hansa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An army fighting for a king of this name lost the Battle of St. Quentin, after which he accepted the Peace of Cateau-Cambresis; that second French king of this name died shortly thereafter in a jousting exhibition. A war between (20 pts)",
        "three prospective rulers of this name forms the core of the French Wars of Religion. A monarch of this name said (10 pts)",
        "“Paris is well worth a mass” in his conversion to Catholicism. For ten points, name this common name of French kings, the fourth of whom founded the House of Bourbon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henry",
        "Henry II, the War of the Three Henrys, Henry IV"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle took place near Horns Reef thanks to Room 40’s success in decoding enemy messages. In this battle, several ships were destroyed during the Run to the South before a reversal and a Run to the North. In this battle, David Beatty’s battlecruisers took heavy losses and were forced to withdraw until John (20 pts)",
        "Jellicoe’s main fleet arrived. This battle occurred despite the fleet-in-being strategy of the German High Seas Fleet, which tried to avoid action against the superior (10 pts)",
        "British Grand Fleet. For ten points, name this major 1916 battle, the largest naval battle of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Jutland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The X-15 research aircraft used liquid oxygen and this substance as rocket propellant. The Ostwald process converts this compound into nitric acid. In (20 pts)",
        "1909, a method of producing this substance using an osmium or iron catalyst and components from the air was developed by (10 pts)",
        "Haber and Bosch, providing saltpeter-starved Germany with explosive material during World War I. For ten points, name this gas with chemical formula NH , important in cleaning 3 supplies and fertilizer."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "anhydrous ammonia",
        "NH before mentioned 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Pope Innocent X called this agreement “null, void...and empty of meaning and effect for all time” in Zelo Domus Dei. This treaty led Spain to acknowledge the independence of the (20 pts)",
        "Dutch Republic and to officially recognize the Treaty of Augsburg’s principle of “cuius regio, eius religio.” This treaty created a namesake system of coexisting sovereign states and was signed at (10 pts)",
        "Osnabruck and Munster. For ten points, name this treaty that ended the Thirty Years’ War."
      ],
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader faced a scandal after pushing for Westland Helicopters to integrate with Sikorsky company rather than the European Agusta firm. The NUM was organized by Michael (20 pts)",
        "Scargill against this leader, who had ordered the closing of 150 coal mines. This leader’s popularity was greatly damaged by the “Community Charge” poll tax and the abolition of free (10 pts)",
        "dairy for school children, prompting her to be known as the “Milk Snatcher.” For ten points, name this Conservative Prime Minister of Britain known as the Iron Lady."
      ],
      "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man fought off Slavs threatening his Billung March and was forced to confront a rebellion of nobles by led by his son Liudolf. In order for this man to marry his wife Adelaide, she had to escape imprisonment by (20 pts)",
        "Berengar II, whom this man later defeated to become King of the Lombards. This ruler stopped the Magyar raids by winning the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lechfeld, leading to the creation of Hungary. Pope John XII crowned, for ten points, what German king who unified Germany and Italy into the Holy Roman Empire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Otto the Great or Otto I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the early stages of this battle, Henry Rawlinson led a successful attack on Bazentin Ridge but was unable to capture High Wood. During this battle, J.R.R. Tolkien came down with a fever and was ruled unfit to fight. Earlier French losses at (20 pts)",
        "Verdun left Douglas Haig in command at this battle. Nearly 20,000 British soldiers died on the first day of this battle, the bloodiest day in British military history. (10 pts)",
        "Tanks were first used at, for ten points, what 1916 battle that failed to break the German line along a French river?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of the Somme or Somme Offensive"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This general defeated the Marathas at the Battle of Assaye in his first major victory. This commander ordered the building of Portugal’s Lines of Torres Vedras, a defense against Andr´e Mass´ena approved by (20 pts)",
        "Lord Castlereagh; two years later, this man routed Auguste Marmont at Salamanca, a key battle of the Peninsular War. In 1815, this commander’s forces were joined by (10 pts)",
        "Gebhard von Blucher’s Prussian troops near Brussels in his most crucial victory. For ten points, name this British general who defeated Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington",
        "either",
        "both underlined portions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Habersham promoted slavery in this colony, whose original charter banned slavery and liquor. The southern border of this colony expanded to the Saint (20 pts)",
        "Marys River after the English victory in the French and Indian War. For its first twenty years, this colony was governed by a Board of Trustees, who had initially intended it as a home for English (10 pts)",
        "debtors. James Oglethorpe founded, for ten points, what US colony that served as a southern buffer between the English colonies and Spanish Florida?"
      ],
      "answer": "Georgia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This military force was sponsored by Pope Sixtus V, who treated it as a crusade and gave its sponsors a subsidy. Prior to this force’s expected deployment of the Army of Flanders, its opponents were (20 pts)",
        "rallied by the Tilbury Speech. The Duke of Medina Sidonia commanded this force, which was designed to prevent interference in the (10 pts)",
        "Netherlands but was devastated at the Battle of Gravelines. Elizabethan England was targeted by, for ten points, what fleet launched in 1588 by Philip II of Spain?"
      ],
      "answer": "the Spanish Armada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler was imprisoned in the fortress of Ku¨strin and nearly executed after he attempted to flee with his boyhood friend Hans Hermann von Katte, but he was captured and forced to watch Katte’s execution. This ruler constructed the (20 pts)",
        "Sansouci [sahn-soo- see] Palace and wrote the Anti-Machiavel, a work influenced by the ideals of Voltaire. This ruler invaded Silesia to begin the War of (10 pts)",
        "Austrian Succession, and fought Maria Theresa of Austria again during the Seven Years War. For ten points, name this King of Prussia known as “the Great.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Frederick the Great or Frederick II of Prussia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. During this event, a series of defenses called fleches [fleshes] were built by Pyotr Bagration, who commanded the left wing under Mikhail Kutuzov. This event, whose casualties were (20 pts)",
        "graphed by Charles Joseph Minard, resulted in its defenders setting fire to their own capital after their loss at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Borodino. A refusal to join the Continental System triggered, for ten points, what 1812 military campaign in which a French emperor conquered, but could not hold, Moscow?"
      ],
      "answer": "French invasion of Russia all three parts required,"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Oster Conspiracy was planned in case this meeting failed to prevent the launch of Operation Green. A letter denouncing this meeting noted that the country was “offered a choice between war and shame. She has chosen shame and will get war.” (20 pts)",
        "Edvard Benes resigned over this meeting, which resulted in the First Vienna Award. This meeting was proclaimed to have secured (10 pts)",
        "“peace for our time” by Neville Chamberlain. For ten points, name this 1938 meeting in which the Allies appeased Germany by allowing Hitler to annex the Sudetenland."
      ],
      "answer": "Munich Conference"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The buildup to this war included the assassination of Kim Ok-gyun, whose corpse was quartered and put on display as a warning, as well as a rebellion by several hundred thousand Donghak peasants. The losing side in this war lost the port city of (20 pts)",
        "Weihaiwei after most of the Beiyang Fleet was devastated at the Battle of the Yalu Rvier. The Triple Intervention by France, Germany,, and (10 pts)",
        "Russia ensured that the Liaodong Peninsula was not claimed by the winners of this war in its ending Treaty of Shimonoseki. For ten points, name this late 19th century war mostly fought in Korea, a victory for the Meiji Emperor over the Qing Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "First Sino-Japanese War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was advised by Mikhail Speransky during his reform of the government and Aleksey Arakcheev during his military reforms. This leader’s failures as commander in chief led him to appoint Mikhail (20 pts)",
        "Kutuzov to lead his army. Confusion over who should succeed this man led to the liberal (10 pts)",
        "Decembrist revolt. This ruler formed the Holy Alliance with Austria and Prussia to preserve Europe after the Congress of Vienna. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who led his country through the Napoleonic Wars."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander I of Russia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this war, French forces captured enemy plans during the Mechelen Incident. During this conflict, the French navy was destroyed at the Battle of Mers el-Kebir to (20 pts)",
        "prevent it from falling into enemy hands. The initial French plan for this conflict involved rushing to the River Dyle to fight with Belgium. After an attack through the Ardennes circumvented the (10 pts)",
        "Maginot Line in this conflict, French troops were encircled at Dunkirk. For ten points, name this war in which France was conquered by Nazi Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "World War II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler briefly interrupted the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies with the creation of the Parthenopaen Republic. This ruler, who organized the Netherlands into the Batavian Republic, forced the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Campo Formio on his rivals. The Confederation of the Rhine was organized by this man as part of a network of client states imposing an economic blockade on (10 pts)",
        "England, the “Continental System.” After Russia refused to agree to this man’s trade policies, this man launched an 1812 invasion. For ten points, name this emperor of France."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to become the first official to resign from the Soviet Politburo after Yegor Ligachev criticized him for allowing dissent as First Secretary. This man rose to fame by stopping the Gang of Eight’s coup with a speech given (20 pts)",
        "atop a tank. This man became the most prominent leader to sign the Belavezha Accords to establish a Commonwealth of Independent States, which formed after the (10 pts)",
        "fall of the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this first president of the Russian Federation and successor of Mikhail Gorbachev."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man defeated Louis-Eugene Cavaignac, the general who put down the June Days uprising, in a presidential election. This man, who employed Baron Haussmann to redesign his capital, sponsored a failed attempt to place (20 pts)",
        "Maximilian on the throne of Mexico. This ruler took personal command in a campaign that enjoyed a major victory at (10 pts)",
        "Solferino, but he was forced to abdicate after his capture at Sedan during a war with Prussia. For ten points, name this last Emperor of France."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon III"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization was named for a chief of the Lenape tribe and accordingly granted the title of “Grand Sachem” upon its leaders. This organization turned off the lights in meetings to stifle dissidents, leading their opposition to be called the (20 pts)",
        "Locofocos. A leader of this organization died in Ludlow Jail after he was deported from Spain; locals in Spain recognized him thanks to (10 pts)",
        "cartoons from Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this notoriously corrupt New York political machine once headed by Boss Tweed."
      ],
      "answer": "Tammany Hall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man provoked the ire of his citizens when he imprisoned William de Braose’s wife after attempting to extract 40,000 marks from William. This man refused to allow Stephen Langton to become Archbishop of (20 pts)",
        "Canterbury, leading Pope Innocent III to excommunicate him. After this man was defeated by French forces at (10 pts)",
        "Bouvines [boo-veen], he was further disgraced when barons cornered him at Runnymede and forced him to give up his unlimited powers. For ten points, name this English king who, in 1215, signed the Magna Carta."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John I of England",
        "John Softsword",
        "Lackland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ziryab introduced toothpaste and deodorant to this peninsula from Baghdad. Hisham II ruled a caliphate on this peninsula where the hajib Al-Mansur secured power. (20 pts)",
        "Taifas were independent kingdoms on this peninsula, where Muhammed XII of the Nasrid Dynasty ruled an emirate. Cardinal Cisneros led a (10 pts)",
        "campaign against Muslims on this peninsula, which was home to the emirates of Cordoba and Granada. For ten points, name this European peninsula that was the subject of the Reconquista by Christian forces fighting for Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Iberian Peninsula"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the Volunteer Army was forced to take the Ice March towards the Kuban region. Two rival governments formed during this war at Omsk and Samara. The (20 pts)",
        "Czechoslovak Legion revolted and controlled most of a railway during this war; another major revolt in this war was launched by sailors at (10 pts)",
        "Kronstadt who were angry at the policies of wartime communism implemented by Leon Trotsky. For ten points, name this war between the Red and White Armies, ending in a Bolshevik triumph."
      ],
      "answer": "Russian Civil War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man ended the revolt of the Obotrites at the battle of Recknitz and secured power after facing a rebellion from Liudolf and Conrad the Red. The creation of the Gero Codex and a scriptorium at Quedlinburg led scholars to name a (20 pts)",
        "“Renaissance” after this man. This man was crowned in 962 by Pope John XII, seven years after a victory over Bulcsu ended (10 pts)",
        "Magyar raids into Western Europe. For ten points, identify this “Great” German Holy Roman Emperor who was victorious at Lechfeld."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Otto the Great",
        "Otto I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Salonika Trial may have been a pretext to execute this event’s planner, a man called “Apis.” This event would have failed if its perpetrator had not stopped near the Latin Bridge at Schiller’s (20 pts)",
        "sandwich shop. The July Ultimatum was issued in the aftermath of this event and threatened that Serbia would be attacked within 48 hours. This event was carried out by the (10 pts)",
        "Black Hand and prompted the armies of Germany and Austria-Hungary to mobilize. For ten points, name this 1914 event perpetrated by Gavrilo Princip that is often considered the spark of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "assassination or murder, shooting, etc. of Archduke Franz Ferdinand do not prompt on partial names"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three members of this family received the Legion of Honor in 1909, including Katharine, who worked as a publicist during their tour of Europe. This family produced the Van Cleve catalog from their home base in Dayton, Ohio, where they operated a (20 pts)",
        "bicycle shop. Two members of this family added a three-axis control system to a (10 pts)",
        "“Flyer” that they tested near Kitty Hawk, North Carolina. For ten points, name this family of engineers that included siblings Katharine, Wilbur, and Orville."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wright family",
        "Katharine, Wilbur, and/or Orville Wright"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a 1997 commercial, a grandmother stops her family’s bickering over the legacy of this leader by remarking that he brought Pizza Hut to their country. This man, who once apologized for comparing West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl to Nazi Joseph Goebbels, was the target of an (20 pts)",
        "unsuccessful coup in August 1991. This recipient of the 1990 Nobel Peace Prize pulled out of a prolonged conflict in (10 pts)",
        "Afghanistan and introduced the perestroika reforms. For ten points, name this last premier of the USSR."
      ],
      "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s hopes of controlling the Mediterranean were dashed after Hayreddin Barbarossa defeated his fleet at Preveza, but this man did check Protestant strength in Germany after defeating the (20 pts)",
        "Schmalkaldic League at Muhlberg. This man’s army innovated the “tercio” system to great effect, defeating rival (10 pts)",
        "Francis I at the Battle of Pavia in the Italian Wars. This man’s reign united the thrones of the Habsburgs and the Valois [val-WAH]. For ten points, name this 16th century ruler of both Spain and the Holy Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor",
        "Charles I of Spain",
        "Carlos I of Spain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event concluded with Patrick Sarsfield’s retreat at the Battle of Reading [redding]. A successful invasion of Torbay, crucial to the beginning of this event, was followed by support from the (20 pts)",
        "Immortal Seven. Organizers of this event had been angered by the Declaration of Indulgence, which sought to achieve religious tolerance for (10 pts)",
        "Catholics. A “Protestant wind” helped facilitate the crossing of the English Channel during, for ten points, what relatively peaceful revolution in which James II was overthrown by William and Mary as rulers of England?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Glorious Revolution",
        "Revolution of 1688"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After a leader of this event was shot, his assassin declared that “I have killed a man, but I am not a murderer;” the courts eventually found Soghomon Tehlirian not guilty of that killing in Berlin. Operation Nemesis sought to assassinate Djemal and (20 pts)",
        "Talaat for this event after the two pashas marched their victims to Deir ez-Zor. The Battle of Sarikamish was blamed on a certain group aiding (10 pts)",
        "Russia in World War I, leading to, for ten points, what genocide perpetrated by the Ottoman government and denied by modern Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Armenian genocide",
        "Armenia alone after “genocide” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s losing commander declared that “we are in the chamber pot” after falling into a trap near La Moncelle. A failed attempt to break out at Floing led to the death of Jean Margueritte during this battle. Officer casualties in this battle forced Auguste (20 pts)",
        "Ducrot to take command before he, too, was replaced by Emmanuel Wimpffen. This battle began when Patrice MacMahon attempted to lift the Siege of Metz, only to be surrounded. The (10 pts)",
        "Second French Empire fell after, for ten points, what battle of the Franco-Prussian War that led to the capture of Napoleon III?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Sedan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man lost at the Battle of Grand Turk in the Turks and Caicos. C. K. Shorter claims that the Bronte family of literary fame changed their surname to associate themselves with this man, the Duke of Bronté. With Lord Jervis, this man attacked (*) Cádiz and led an amphibious attack on Santa Cruz de Tenerife. On the Victory, this man engaged the Bucentaure and signaled, \"England expects (*) that every man will do his duty.” For ten points, name this British admiral who was killed at Trafalgar."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Horatio Nelson",
        "1st Viscount Nelson,",
        "1st Duke of Bronté before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man sent \"sincere congratulations\" that an attack of \"armed hordes\" had been stopped \"without appealing to friendly powers for help.” In 1895, this man was compelled to send a cruiser to Delagoa Bay, and a telegram from him to Johannes (*) Kruger was possibly written by Adolf Marschall von Bieberstein. In the Daily Telegraph Affair, this man called the English \"mad as March hares.” Before World War One, this man sent (*) Nicholas II the Willy-Nicky letters. For ten points, name this German Kaiser."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wilhelm II",
        "William II 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement was aided by Lucas Cranach, who helped create artistic propaganda to spread its beliefs. This movement’s focus on vernacular writing helped achieve a higher level of literacy in Europe. Metaphorically, this movement hatched the egg that (20 pts)",
        "Erasmus laid. In 1531, the Peace of Augsburg helped achieve the goals of this movement which began after a German (10 pts)",
        "monk wrote against the practice of indulgences. For ten points, name this movement against the Catholic Church, started in 1517 by Martin Luther."
      ],
      "answer": "Protestant Reformation"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1296, this man, whose nickname was “Milione” [[meel-YONE-eh]] was captured during a war with Genoa. While in prison, this man's cellmate was the author of Romance of King Arthur, a Pisan known as Rusticiano. Historians have accused this man of (20 pts)",
        "exaggeration in stories such as having accompanied Princess Kokochin to Persia. This Italian was welcomed at the court of Kublai (10 pts)",
        "Khan, and later provided Europeans with their first in-depth information about Far Eastern culture. For ten points, name this Venetian explorer, namesake of a swimming pool game."
      ],
      "answer": "Marco Polo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The paladin Oliver de Vienne tells this man, his brother-in-law, that “Reasonableness is to be preferred to recklessness\" before succumbing to his wounds. The only historical mention of this otherwise literary figure is found in Vita Karoli Magni by (20 pts)",
        "Einhard, who describes this man as a prefect of Brittany. This man mortally wounds the Saracen King Marsile during the climactic battle of (10 pts)",
        "Roncevaux Pass. For ten points, name this officer of Charlemagne who blew a horn made of an elephant tusk, the protagonist of an 11th century French “Song.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Rolando",
        "Orlando"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The so-called \"English Achilles,\" John Talbot, led a campaign in this century which ended with the disastrous Battle of Castillon [[cah-steh-YOHN]], leading to the loss of (20 pts)",
        "Aquitaine. English longbowmen and the deployment of wooden stakes by the British proved vital at the Battle of Agincourt [[ah-jinn-KOHR]], a clash during this century. The Hundred Years' War (10 pts)",
        "ended in, for ten points, what century of the late Middle Ages?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fifteenth Century",
        "1400s"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Like his Russian cousin some years later, this man received a dragon tattoo on his arm while visiting Japan in 1881. During this man's rule, the Parliament Act cemented the House of Commons' superiority to the House of Lords, and the Free State of Ireland became (*) independent. This man's tour of gravesites in Belgium was memorialized in Rudyard Kipling's long poem The King's Pilgrimage. (*) For ten points, name this ruler of Great Britain during World War One."
      ],
      "answer": "George V"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Antikythera [[AN-tih-kih-THEER-uh]] mechanism is believed to be the oldest example of an analogue type of this device. The Difference Engine was (20 pts)",
        "a prototype of one of these devices built by Charles Babbage. German engineer Konrad Zuse [[ZOO-suh]] developed the Z3, the first programmable digital example of these devices, during World War (10 pts)",
        "Two. For ten points, name these devices that rapidly carry out mathematical operations, the \"science\" for which was pioneered by Alan Turing."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Computers",
        "Analogue Computers",
        "or Electromechanical Computer",
        "or Computer Science"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man urged the common British person to abandon so-called \"dying metaphors\" in his essay \"Politics and the English Language.\" This writer's participation in the POUM (*) party's militia during the Spanish Civil War inspired his autobiographical Homage to Catalonia. This man's time as police sub-commandant in British Burma inspired his short story \"Shooting an Elephant.\" The rise of totalitarianism (*) inspired, for ten points, which British writer's 1984 and Animal Farm?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Orwell",
        "Eric Arthur Blair"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) \"Mad Jack\" Churchill entered battle carrying one of these instruments, using it to signal attack orders to his fellow commandos during operations. James Reid was executed for playing this instrument during the Battle of Culloden [[kuh-LAH-den]] in (20 pts)",
        "the Jacobite [[JAK-oh-bite]] Rising, with the British brandishing this instrument as a \"weapon of war.\" Contemporary historian George Buchanan reports that this aerophonic instrument replaced the trumpet in warfare during in the 1600s. The Highlanders (10 pts)",
        "of Scotland introduced, for ten points, which woodwind instrument?"
      ],
      "answer": "Bagpipes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1979, the Wetzel [[VEHT-zull]] family escaped East Germany using one of these objects after years of planning. The first-ever intercontinental ranged weapon used this technology and was known as Fu-Go (20 pts)",
        "by the Japanese. French brothers Joseph-Michel and Jacques-Étienne Montgolfier [[mohnt-gahl-FYEH]] undertook the first manned flight of this technology, which was used for reconnaissance at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Fleurus [[floo-ROO]]. For ten points, name these inflatable transports which Nadar used to take aerial photographs of Paris."
      ],
      "answer": "Hot-Air Balloon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Myths about this location were discredited by Frantz Funck-Brentano [[foonk- bren-TAH-noh]]. A large plaster elephant was placed at this location by Napoleon, though it was replaced by the July Column. (20 pts)",
        "Palloy the Patriot demolished this location, which was defended by Bernard Rene de Launay [[reh-neh-duh-law-NAY]] alongside the Swiss Guard who were cut down by a (10 pts)",
        "mob. For ten points, name this Parisian fortress and prison destroyed at the beginning of the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "The Bastille Saint-Antoine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was born in the Wallowa [[wall-OW-ah]] Valley with a name meaning \"Thunder Rolling Down the Mountain.\" This man’s heart was “sick and sad” in 1877 after he failed to escape into (20 pts)",
        "Canada and was forced to surrender to U.S. soldiers led by Nelson Miles. This man was a leader of a tribe that is often known by a two-word (10 pts)",
        "French phrase meaning “pierced nose.” For ten points, name this Nez Percé [[NEZ \"PURSE\"]] chief who vowed “I will fight no more forever.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Chief Joseph"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Li Mi of the Sui [[SWEH]] Dynasty constructed 300 of the \"Whirlwind\" variety of these machines to be placed on ships. During the Hrushevskoho [[hroo-shehv- SKOH-hoh]] Street riots, a Kievan mob built one of these machines to hurl Molotov (*) cocktails at government buildings. The Mangonel was an early form of this siege engine brought from China, arriving in Medieval (*) Europe by the 9th century. For ten points, what siege engine used a counterweight to fling objects?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Trebuchet or Trebucket",
        "specific examples, such as the Traction Trebuchet",
        "Counterpoise Trebucet",
        "Mangonel before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man delivered a speech condemning Operation Danube, declaring it was a \"grave error and constituted a serious danger to peace in Europe.\" One of this man's first actions as head of state was to pass Decree 770 in order to boost (20 pts)",
        "population by making abortion illegal. Following this man's overthrow, he and his wife were found guilty of corruption and (10 pts)",
        "genocide and were sentenced to death by the National Salvation Front. For ten points, name this Romanian communist dictator."
      ],
      "answer": "Nicolae Ceaușescu ]"
    }
  ]
}